LD字幕组
林氏王朝字幕组出品
微博地址：http://weibo.com/jl7ld
翻译：奥利奥   远远的咕咕   大萌    回锅肉JJYY    简单计划
校对：远远的咕咕   简单计划
后期效果：远远的咕咕
禁止将本字幕用于商业用途
转载请注明 林氏王朝字幕组
当时已经是我到球队后的第二还是第三场主场比赛了
Jeremy lin: So it was like my second or third home game,
我甚至还从未上过场
And I hadn't even been in a game yet,
当我试图进入球馆时
And I had tried to get in the gym,
他们拦住我
And they stopped me.
他们说
And they were like,
“抱歉，这里是球员入口”
"oh, sorry, this is the players' entrance."
我说，“我知道啊”
I was like, "I know."
那个保安就困惑地看着我
He looked at me confused,
于是我也困惑地看着他
And then so I was looking at him confused.
然后他说
And then he was like,
“哦，抱歉，你是队上的训练师吗？”
"oh, I'm sorry. Are you a trainer?"
我站在那不知道说什么好
And I was just kind of just like standing there.
然后另一个保安走过来
And then another security guard came over
对着之前那个耳语道，“他应该是在队上打球的”
And, like, whispered, "I think he plays on the team."
现在上场的是后卫...
At guard it's...
十七号，林书豪！
Number 17, jeremy lin!
书豪
Hey, jeremy.
Hi.
没有人认为他会打球
Nobody thought he could play.
他需要为所得的一切而战
He had to fight for everything that he got.
你很少能有这种感觉：你见证了
It's not often you think you've seen something
联盟中罕见的奇迹
You couldn't possibly see in the nba.
林投篮！
Lin puts it up!
进了！
Bang!
等等，这小子是谁？
Wait a minute. Who's this kid?
等等，他从哪冒出来的？
Wait. Where's he from?
等等，落选秀？
Wait. Not drafted?
等等，被多少球队裁掉过？
Wait. How many teams waived him?
当他打球时
When this guy is playing,
勇士队不知道他这么棒
And golden state doesn't know he's any good,
火箭队不知道他这么棒
Houston doesn't know he's any good,
我不得不想，难道是因为
I got to imagine that something has to do with
他看上去不像个打球的好手
He doesn't look the part.
林书豪从默默无闻走到伟大
Jeremy lin came from nothing to greatness.
嘿，这小子给所有孩子以希望
Hey, this kid is giving hope to all those kids
那些认为自己永远不会有机会的孩子
That think, "never could I have a chance."
我一直对自己说，我的进步历程会是这样
I always told myself my progression is gonna be
从进入轮换，到成为首发控卫
Become a rotation player, become a starting point guard,
然后赢得NBA总冠军
And then win an nba championship.
人们听到后肯定会嘲笑我
And people are definitely gonna laugh when they hear that.
但是有朝一日这一切成真时
You know, they're not gonna be laughing
他们就不会再笑了
If it actually happens.
新泽西网队
对
纽约尼克斯
2012年2月4日
防守！
De-fense!
48个小时内，林书豪就会被裁掉
很可能就此终结他的NBA事业
并结束他的一生梦想
尼克斯队的山姆波特，个人第二次犯规
New york foul is on shumpert, his second.
现在他得下场休息会儿了
And now, he'll have to take a seat,
看看谁要上场了
And, again, mike, look who's coming in.
是林书豪，你可以听到球迷的大声欢呼
Jeremy lin, and you hear a pretty big ovation.
我知道是神在安排这一切
Jeremy: I know god orchestrated this whole thing.
因为太多事情在我的掌控之外
There's just too much out of my control.
而且它们发生的方式是那样的不可思议
And just the way it happened is just miraculous.
书豪！
Jeremy!
是真的
It's actually true.
在我大概八、九岁后
After, I think, age maybe 8 or 9,
我们换掉了电视
We got rid of the tv,
我们会在季后赛时看比赛
And we would just get it during the playoffs.
我们会在家看
We would watch it in the house
然后在后院
And then, in the backyard,
有扇玻璃门，外面有个篮筐
There's a glass door and a hoop outside,
我们会在外面透过窗子看
So we would just watch through the window,
然后在场间休息或是暂停时
And then any time there was,like, a break or a time-out,
我们会出去模仿
We'd go out, and we'd do the exact move
刚刚球场上出现过的动作
That just happened.
基本上就全部都是模仿乔丹
And it was pretty much all just copying michael jordan
并且看到他取得胜利
And watching him win.
我们热爱那种观看比赛的方式
And so we loved watching basketball that way,
那一直是我的一个梦想
And it was always a dream of mine,
但我从未想过它会变成现实
But I didn't actually think it would be a reality.
你在哪搞到这个的？
Where did you get this done?
在市中心
是吗？在格林威治村？
Down town.
Oh, yeah? Down in the village?
来看看这个
Can you take a look? Look at this.
让我看看..背上这是..
Let me see what you... This is the back of...
怎么样？
What do you think?
非常棒
Beautifully done.
Yeah.
无与林比
Lintastic.
谢谢
Thank you.
所有孩子都有自己的梦想
Every kid has a dream.
有些想当消防员，有些想当宇航员
Some want to be a fireman, others an astronaut.
大多数时候，梦想只是梦而已
Most of the time, dreams are just dreams.
这个梦始于加州帕罗奥托
This dream starts in palo alto, california,
旧金山的一片郊区
A suburb of san francisco,
在这里，一个年轻人学习信仰
Where a young man learns about faith,
坚韧与机遇
Perseverance, and opportunity.
茄子！
Cheese!
在台湾，我们只重视学习，我们并不重视打球
那时候上完班之后，每次就很累，觉得很累
林明杰
林书豪的爸爸
我在想说，我看篮球看了这么多，特别是NBA
那我就开始练习打篮球
我自己练习了五年，像怎么运球，怎么投篮
怎么上篮，我自己练了五年各式各样的
而且我特别喜欢练习的就是贾巴尔的勾手
我如果有小孩子
在他们小时候一定要开始
带他们一起打篮球
当爸爸带我们去基督教青年会打球时
Joshua lin: My dad was taking us to the ymca.
我们还在上小学
We were still, like, in elementary school.
周一、三、五球馆开放
There's like open gym Monday,Wednesday, fridays,
林书雅
林书豪的哥哥
从晚上七点半到九点半
From like 7:30 to 9:30.
当时我们放学回家后
And we would just come home from school,
我们会尽快做完作业
And we would just all do our homework as fast as possible.
当有人不能完成作业时
And then when someone couldn't finish their assignment,
我们会互相帮助
Then we would go and help them,
如果我做不完
So if I couldn't finish,
我哥就会来帮我
Josh would come over and help me.
如果弟弟做不完
If joe couldn't finish,
我们就会去帮他
You know, we would go over and help joe.
这是我们一直学到的一点
That's everything we've always known is just, you know,
就是我们是兄弟，我们是彼此最好的朋友
Having each other and being best friends with each other.
我当时不喜欢弹钢琴
I didn't want to play the piano,
我弹得很糟
And I was horrible at the piano.
每年的表演会上
Like, every year,the recital would come around,
我都会弹同一首曲子
And I'd be pretty much playing the same song.
我的父母就觉得这样不行
And they were just like, "this is not working.
完全是在浪费钱
"I'm wasting my money.
这孩子只爱打篮球
"all he does is play basketball,
那就让他打篮球吧
So let's just let him play basketball."
当我们逐渐爱上这项运动时
As we grew to love the game,
我妈妈给予了巨大支持
My mom becamea huge supporter.
我想她能看出我们是真爱篮球
I think she could just see that we loved basketball,
看出我们心中的热爱与激情
That we were passionate about it.
而她全心爱着我们
And she's passionate about us
所以无论我们想做什么
So whatever we wanted to do,
她总是愿意支持我们
She always wanted to support us.
她总是开车送大家，她是全队的家长
She always drove. She was always a team parent
在所有二哥和我打过的
For every njb, aau
林书伟
林书豪的弟弟
全国青少年篮球联赛（NJB）和
业余体育联盟比赛（AAU）
That jeremy played for, that I played for.
她总会出现在左右
She was always there.
支持着我们
She was always supporting us.
不是所有的母亲，尤其是亚裔母亲
You know, not every mom, asian mom especially,
会支持孩子打篮球
Is gonna support their child playing basketball.
Cheese!
Hi!
坚强的意志
Strong will.
坚强的意志?
Strong will?
坚强的意志
Strong will.
如果他想要什么东西
If he wants something,
他会竭尽所能去得到
He will do anything to get that thing.
他会把头往地上撞
So he will knock his head on the ground.
他会故意摔倒
He will just make himself fall.
他会做一切事情来试图得到自己想要的东西
He will do anything to get what he wants.
在我成长过程中，我的家庭总是强调神是首位的
Growing up, my family always emphasized god first,
学业其次，运动第三
School second, athletics third.
刚开始，他们并不确定
In the beginning, they weren't sure
我能打多久的篮球
How long I could play basketball.
他们就是决定顺其自然
They were just gonna ride it out
尽可能地享受篮球带来的快乐
And have fun with it as long as we could.
我当时受邀前往一场
帕罗奥托的基督教青年会联赛
Jim sutter: I got invited to a y league game in palo alto.
他当时就是一个小小孩
And he's just this little kid.
吉姆· 萨特
AAU球队METRO MIRAGE的教练
你不会想到
You know, you wouldn't think it,
他的得分能力这么出色
But he just scored the basketball so well.
第一场比赛时
The first tournament we played,
他开始狂投三分
And he just starts just raining 3-pointers.
Yeah!
他们说我叫得太大声了
They will say I am so loud,
因为我会不停喊“防守！”
Because I will keep talking, "defense!"
或是“抢篮板！”
You know, "get a rebound!"
Yeah!
当然他妈妈当时会那样
Of course, mom's like,
不停喊“他得了多少分？”
"how many points
did he score?"
她会说，“我告诉过你他棒极了吧”
She'd say, "I told you he was pretty good."
我会说，“我知道，我知道他很棒”
I go, "I know. I know he's pretty good."
当时所有AAU的球队都不要书豪
All the aau team, they never want jeremy,
即便他是当时最棒的控卫
Even though he's the best point guard at that time.
只有这一支球队
Only this particular aau,
Metro Mirage非常想要书豪为他们打球
Metro mirage, want him so bad.
耶，书豪！
Yeah, jeremy!
我喜欢处在这个被轻视的位置
I love being the underdog
因为这是我习惯的角色
Just because it's just what I'm used to.
也许我在联盟中会打得不错
You know, I would be good in this league,
但人们会说
And then people would say,
“但是他在这个联盟中不可能打好的”
"oh, but he can't play well in this league."
每次书豪对位某个人们都说棒的球员
Every time jeremy play against somebody who people say is good,
如果书豪打得更好
If jeremy played better,
他们就会开始想，其实是这人不行
Then they start thinking, "that person's not good."
而不会肯定书豪打得好
They don't give jeremy credit.
有一种十四块钱的超大玉米饼
There's a $14 extra-large burrito
就像这么大
That's like this.
我的天，你一定得买那个吃
Oh, my gosh, you should totally get that.
书豪，你要买这个大的吗？
Jeremy, you gonna get the big one?
是的
Jeremy: Yeah.
人与食物大对决
Man versus food.
我要开启野兽模式了
I'm about to beast this.
我也不知道我是怎么长这么高的
Jeremy: I don't know how I got so tall, dude.
我食量很大
I ate a lot.
我会去吊单杠
I would hang
from monkey bars.
我会躺在床沿想着
Um, I would lie off the edge of my bed thinking
重力会把我拉长
That gravity would pull me and make me taller.
当我高一时我只有一米六左右
When I was 5'3" as a freshman in high school,
我记得，我妈妈也记得
I remember--my mom remembers this, too--
每天早上我钻进车里时
I would get in the car every single day
我都会说，“你们为什么不长高点？”
And I'd be like, "why aren't you taller?"
这就是我一直这么矮的原因
Like, "this is why I'm so short."
我妈妈会说，“要怪就怪你爸”
She always said, "blame your dad.
“我可不矮”
I'm not that short."
她有差不多一米六八
She's 5'6".
对于亚裔女性来说这挺高的
For an asian woman, that's pretty tall.
我爸爸同样是一米六八
And my dad's also 5'6".
帕罗奥图中学
我想我对他在篮球上的最大影响
I think my biggest influence on him as a player,
我们聊得最多的话题
The most constant dominant conversation we had
彼得·迪潘布洛克
帕罗奥图中学1997-2008篮球教练
是他要为其他队员创造机会
Was him creating for others.
高中的时候，他知道他能够在场上
In high school, he knew he could get by
好好利用他的天赋
And do well on his talent.
许多孩子，特别是他
A lot of kids, and him especially,
一心想着得分
It was all about scoring.
而我跟他聊得最多的
And my constant conversation,
也是他给我的最大难题
My constant challenge with him was,
“书豪，你有创造机会的能力
"jeremy, you're a creator.
“你真的可以当领头人
"you could really be the man
只要你明白自己是个怎样的球员”
If you just embraced who you are as a player."
在他高一那年
During his junior year,
林书豪在学校的维京人队里崭露头角
Jeremy emerged as the vikings' star.
随着一场场比赛，他的技术和自信渐长
With every game, his skills and confidence grew,
但他的自负也随之而长
But so did his ego.
有一段时间我们甚至打出30胜1负的成绩
We were like 30 and 1 at one point.
那时候我们所向披靡
We were killing everybody.
我开始自我膨胀
I was starting to get a big head,
觉得自己很了不起
Thinking I was sweet and everything,
结果后来我受伤了
And then I get hurt.
高中时林书豪习惯
Jeremy had a tradition of shooting around
在比赛的前一晚练球
The night before his high school games.
但是在州半决赛的前一晚
But on the eve of the state semifinal game,
高中的体育馆关门了
The high school gym was closed,
林在本地的基督教青年会打了场即兴的比赛
And jeremy played in a pick-up game at his local ymca.
当晚，林书豪扭伤了脚踝
That night, jeremy fractured his ankle,
他的信念将受到考验
And his faith would be tested.
我几乎崩溃了
I just pretty much broke down.
我忍不住大哭
Um, I broke down crying.
在那之前，我从未经历过严重的打击
Up until then, like, I'd never gone through any serious tragedy.
那次是我当时经历过最糟的事情
That was the worst thing that ever happened to me.
由于林书豪无法上场
With jeremy on the bench,
维京人队获得冠军的希望迅速陨灭了
The vikings' hopes for a state championship quickly faded.
你知道，对于一个高中生来说
You know, from a high schooler's perspective,
那是非常大的打击
That's like everything.
我告诉他退后一步
I told him to take a step back
用更广阔的视角来看
And to look at it from a bigger perspective.
我记得我哥哥给我发了一封很长的信
I remember my brother sent me this really long letter.
他谈到神如何给予和收回
He talks about how god gives and takes away.
神拿走了我那时特别在乎的东西
And so god took what I really cared about at that time
来说明，离开神
To show me that I can't do what I want to do,
我就不能完成我的愿望
I can't accomplish what I want to accomplish without him,
这个世界上，在我的生命里
And that nothing in this world, in my life,
没有什么不是按照神的旨意发生的
Will happen that's not according to his plan.
当大卫面对巨人歌利亚时
When david faced goliath,
他并不知道结果
He didn't know the outcome,
但他对神有热忱
But he was zealous for the living god.
我知道书豪把神放在第一位
With jeremy, I know he puts the order, god first,
其次是家人，第三是篮球
Family second, basketball third.
现在他会告诉你
And he'll tell you this now at least.
史提芬·陈
林书豪的牧师
回顾过去，神主宰着这一切
Looking back, it's more of, god is in all those things.
高中时，他很谦虚
And in high school, he was humbled.
他知道不能以一己之力完成所有事情
He learned that he couldn't do everything himself.
阿门
Amen
他只能信赖神
And he could only put his faith in god.
我告诉自己
I told myself,
我只剩一年确定可以打篮球了
I have one year left of guaranteed basketball.
我要全力以赴
I said I'm gonna do everything I can,
我将力拼到底
And I'm gonna go out fighting,
我要确保我们还会回到这里
And I'm gonna make sure that we get back here.
他的镇定是一个高四学生少有的
He had unusual poise for a high school senior,
特别地自信
Unusual confidence.
他身上有某种东西让我明白
There was something about him that I could see
米驰·史提芬
国内专栏作家
为什么他在球场上是个好领袖
Why he was a great leader on the court,
因为你会不自觉被他吸引
'cause you're just driven to him.
你能感觉到他的心跳
You can feel his heartbeat.
每次他们比分很接近的时候
Every close game they had,
林书豪就会有关键的表现
Jeremy lin was making a big play.
每次的方式都不一样
And it was every different way--
比赛最后关头的三分，或者抢断
A 3-pointer, a steal at the end of the game.
但每次都有他的参与
But every one, he was in the middle of.
他是那个挺身而出的人
He was the guy doing it.
林从右侧跳投
Lin takes a jump shot right side.
中了！
Hits!
漂亮的跳投
Oh, a nice jump shot.
林的三分，有了！
Lin for 3. Buries it!
没有什么能够阻止林书豪
Nothing was going to stop jeremy
把他的球队带回到州决赛
From getting his team back to the state championship,
很快，帕罗奥图中学面对着自己的巨人歌利亚
And, soon enough, palo alto faced goliath.
在阿科球馆里的对阵双方
是马特蒂中学和帕罗奥图中学
Announcer: Inside arco arena, it's mater dei and palo alto.
这是加州校际联盟第二分区的州冠军决赛
It's the cif division ii state championship
预告之后马上开始
Just moments away from tip-off.
我想很多人都认为
I think a lot of people just assumed
能来到州冠军决赛
That getting to the state championship game,
帕罗奥图中学已经满足了
Palo alto would be satisfied with.
林书豪已经满足了
Jeremy lin would be satisfied with it.
和马特蒂中学的比赛
And it was just much more of a formality
不过是走个形式罢了
When they played mater dei high school.
南加州的学校排名都很靠前
Southern california schools dominate the rankings.
都是强队
They're the powers that be.
在郊区的帕罗奥图中学，不怎么样
Palo alto, out in the suburbs, not so much.
人人都说，马特蒂中学肯定赢
Everybody said mater dei was the team,
马特蒂中学优势很大
Mater dei is the big dog.
马特蒂中学在全国排名11位
Mater dei, number 11 in the country.
赛前的一整个星期
The whole week leading up to the game,
我都在想，我们怎么才能抢到篮板？
It was just like, "how we gonna get a rebound?
怎么才能打好？
How we gonna be able to play?"
我记得在校园里走时
I remember walking around campus,
很多记者跑来问
And there are all these reporters.
你觉得你们能赢？
And they'd be like, "oh, you think you can win?"
你们要怎么打赢他们？
Like, "how you gonna beat 'em?"
每个人，包括我的朋友都问我
And everyone's asking me, my friends were asking me.
后来当他们问“你觉得你们能打赢他们？”
By the end, they're like, "you think you can beat 'em?"
我就说：“来看比赛就知道了。”
I was like, "man, just come to the game and watch."
马特蒂中学不仅有
Along with mater dei's
引以为傲的历史和强大的名气
Decorated history and dominant reputation,
这支校队还有8名身高1.98米以上的球员
This varsity team had 8 players over 6'6".
我听到对手是帕罗奥图时，还松了口气
I was kindof relieved that we were playing palo alto,
但我越看他们的录像，越感觉到
But the more I watched them on tape, I just had a feeling.
格瑞·麦克奈
马特蒂高中篮球教练
你还别说
You know what?
这些小伙子比我想象的要厉害
These guys are better than I thought.
如果没两下子，是不可能打到州决赛的
You know, you don't get to the state finals by not being good.
林的球
Here's lin.
来个好球吧，他做到了
Needs something good, and he finally got it.
教练：我们一点都没被镇住
Diepenbrock: We were not intimidated at all
真的全力以赴打好比赛
And really came out playing our game.
林的球，这就是他们说的
Here's lin. Oh, there's that quick first step
很快的第一步
That they talked about.
帕罗奥图打了一波9比2，到此为止
Palo alto on a 9-2 run, and that's over.
那孩子三分厉害
That kid can throw the triple.
从纸面上所有人都会说无论从体格、
Everybody on paper would say the size,
运动能力还是速度，帝王队（对手球队名）都更强
The athleticism, the quickness is with the monarchs,
但从斗志来说，维京人队更胜一筹
But it's the heart that is with the vikings,
今晚他们的斗志得到充分的体现
And their heart has been on display so far tonight.
比赛的最后
Mcknight: At the end of the game,
他在关键的时刻投进了重要的球
He hit the big shots at the big moments.
林的球
Here's lin.
没有投中距离，直接攻击篮筐！
Without that 7-footer, he can go to the rack!
当比赛悬于一线时，他接管了比赛
When the game was on the line, yeah, he took over.
进攻时间只剩4秒了
Four seconds on the shot clock,
林不得不远距离投篮
And lin is gonna have to launch a 25-footer.
中了！
Oh, it went in!
有意安排的吗？我看不像
Did he call that? I think he called that.
是自然发生的
It happened.
没有人期望他们能战胜帝王队
No one gave them a prayer to be on the floor
因为他们没有帝王队所拥有的
With the athletes and the thoroughbreds
精心培养的运动人才
That the monarchs have.
到达最高点，这是最棒的感觉
It's the best feeling to go out on top.
这就是美梦成真
I mean, it is a dream come true.
这就是为什么我喜欢高中篮球
It's why we love high school basketball
因为这样的笑脸
Because of faces like that.
教练：当我纵观这一切
Diepenbrock: When I really looked at everything,
一个篮球运动员
Everything a basketball player
能够为他自己
Could do for himself individually
为球队做的一切
And for a team,
林书豪都是这里最好的球员
Jeremy lin was the best player here,
可是大学并没有争着要他
But yet colleges weren't clamoring for him.
他不符合固有的模式
He just didn't fit the mold.
高中毕业时
After my senior year,
我非常想在大学打篮球
I was just dying to play in college,
15.4分
6.2助攻
4.2抢断
北加州第二分区
年度最佳球员
全加州第一阵容球员
而且觉得自己有这个实力
And I felt like I deserved it.
我记得那个过程很长
I remember it was just a very long process,
感觉很沮丧，因为我问了一间又一间的
Very frustrating,because I was going
太平洋十校联盟的院校
From pac 10 school to pac 10 school.
太平洋十校联盟：是一个美国西部的大学体育联盟，
成员包括斯坦福大学等名校，现已改名为太平洋十二校联盟
我甚至得不到
I couldn't even get
第三分区的学校青睐
Some division iii schools to look at me.
而我特别想去斯坦福大学
And I was dying to go to stanford.
我常常去他们学校打球
Um, I would go there and play with them all the time.
我会问他们的教练
I would always ask their coach, you know,
我怎样才能到你队里打球？
"what can I do to play for you?"
是，我常说如果我是黑人
Yeah, I've always said, if I was black,
我会得到第一分区学校的奖学金
I would have gotten a d-1 scholarship,
但那只是我的个人意见
But that's my personal opinion.
教练：他是个亚裔孩子
Diepenbrock: Well, he's an asian kid.
没有两米身高的亚裔孩子
He's an asian kid, and he's not 7-foot tall.
你很少见到亚裔的控卫
And you don't see a lot of asian point guards
能进入第一分区的篮球队
Making it in division I basketball.
想法很简单，但那就是他们的想法
Such a simple kind of thought, but that was the thinking.
我会说，他和我有共鸣
I say...I say he's relatable.
范振书亚
林书豪的朋友
他是我见过最脚踏实地的人之一
He's one of the most down-to-earth guys I know.
我们总是开玩笑
We're always joking around.
总是互相搞恶作剧
We're always, you know, pranking on each other.
你看到那些蓝色的点缀吗？
Um, did you see the blue accented stuff?
我看到啊，你喜欢那种蓝色？
I did see it. You like that blue?
是，我很喜欢那种蓝色
Yeah. I really like that blue,
因为我走进来时
'cause when I walk in,
我不要只有黑和白
I don't want it to be like black, white, black.
我要大家都惊叹
I want people to be like, "dang."
哇，这个
Oh, shoot, son.
不同的墙壁需要不同的点缀
Different walls need different accents.
这些是清仓甩卖的
These are clearance.
哇，看这个
Yeah, dang, look at that.
看，才10美元
Look at this. 10 bucks.
人们跟他一起的时候
I think when people hang out with him,
他们会发现
They just realize he's just...
他就是个普通人
You know, he's human.
听着不错，好，再见
Sounds good. All right, see you later, bro.
虽然被评为年度最佳球员
Despite being named player of the year
还获得了加州冠军
And winning a state championship,
林书豪得到的唯一一份
Jeremy's only offer
能够打篮球的大学录取通知
To play basketball on the collegiate level
是一所“小”学校
Was from a small university
哈佛
Called harvard.
第一天上课
My first day at class,
我被彻底吓着了
I was just super-intimidated.
我去参加数学分班测验
I went and took my math placement test,
他们说，如果你不会做
And they were like, "if you don't know how to do this,
可以交卷走人
Feel free to turn it in and leave."
我看着试卷，心想
I looked at it and I was, like,
天呐，我啥也看不懂
"dude, I don't know what's going on here."
于是我交了卷
So I turned it in, and I was,
我大概是第二个交卷的
Like, maybe the second person who turned it in.
我心想，天，我在哈佛的
I was like, "man, I just, like,
第一场测验就挂了
Failed my first test at harvard."
第二天，我们进行中文分班测验
The next day, we had the chinese placement test,
然后他们说
And they gave us the test, and they're like,
如果你读不懂，可以交卷
"if you can't read it, just turn it in."
我读不懂啊，就又交卷了
I couldn't read it, so I turned it in again,
那是连续两次测验挂掉
And that was back-to-back failed tests
我甚至一个答案都写不出
Without even filling in an answer.
我在电话里跟我妈妈说
I called my mom, I was like, "man,
以后估计很难熬了，要做好心理准备
This is gonna be pretty tough, so just get ready."
很大程度上，林书豪去哈佛
In a lot of ways, jeremy lin going to harvard
是符合逻辑的
Was a very logical thing.
哈佛有23名
There were 23 asian-americans at harvard
姓林的亚裔学生
Whose last name was lin.
所以林进入哈佛
And so for jeremy lin to show up at harvard,
作为亚裔的孩子
Being this asian-american kid,
数学成绩好
Who had a perfect math sat ii score was,
你也知道，并不少见
You know, nothing rare.
但是他打篮球很厉害的这个事实（却很特别）
But the fact that he was amazing at this game,
问题是他如何融入哈佛？
The question was then how did he fit in at harvard?
汤米·艾默科
There is tommy amaker,
1987年毕业于杜克大学（篮球名校）
1987 graduate of duke, of course,
这是在哈佛的第一年
First year at harvard,
已经有11年的主教练经验
11th year overall as a head coach,
180场胜利
180 career wins.
随着前密歇根大学的教练汤米·艾默科的到来
With the hiring of former michigan coach tommy amaker,
哈佛决心走进
Harvard was committed to a new era
篮球上的新时代
In their basketball program.
艾默科在杜克大学是明星球员
Amaker was a star player at duke university,
后来当了九年的助教
Then spent nine years as an assistant coach
辅佐传奇教练迈克·沙舍夫斯基（老K教练）
To the legendary mike krzyzewski.
哈佛的篮球版图
The basketball landscape at harvard
正准备改头换面
Was about to be transformed,
而林书豪是排头兵
And jeremy was leading the charge.
我知道我们有些特别的因素
We knew we had something pretty interesting,
特别是林书豪
Especially with jeremy,
因为首先他训练特别刻苦
Because of how hard he worked, first of all,
而且篮球对他而言非常重要
And how important basketball was to him.
还有就是他的天赋
And then his talent.
我认为他被大大地低估了
I think he was very much underrated,
我认为他想按照
And I think he wanted to play in the style
我们推行的
And the system, you know,
风格和系统打球
That we weregonna implement,
也就是高能量的风格
Which is gonna be high octane.
他的球风很强硬
And he's a hard-charging,
侵略性强，无所畏惧
Aggressive, fearless player.
林书豪断球
A steal by jeremy lin.
轻松扣篮
He's gonna go in for the easy jam.
抬头看
Looking up ahead,
林撕裂了防守并成功上篮！
Lin splits defenders and lays it in!
我做教练15年
In my 15 years of coaching,
在杜克大学打了4年球
My four years at duke,
我从来没见过任何人
I've never seen anybody
像林书豪那么努力
Work as diligent and as hard as jeremy.
他每天都来，认真训练
He came in every day and put the work in.
肯尼·布雷肯尼
哈佛大学2007-2011男篮助教
我们每天看录像
We watched film every day.
我们训练前后也在练习
We did work before and after practice.
他非常勤奋
He busted his tail,
我们要求他做的，他都做到了
And he did all the things that we asked him to do.
弧顶出手，大三分，林书豪！
Top of the circle, deep 3, jeremy lin!
似乎比赛场面越大，他打得越好
It seems the bigger the game, the better he played.
这是一场大东部的篮球赛
It's big east basketball,
排名第13的康涅狄格大学哈士奇队
对阵哈佛大学的猩红队
As the 13th ranked uconn huskies host the crimson of harvard.
今天要注意的是林书豪
Now, keep an eye on jeremy lin today.
这样的球员
This is the type of player
能够只手帮助猩红队
That can single-handedly help the crimson
起死回生
Pull off a miraculous upset.
艾默科：他是场上最棒的球员
Amaker: He was the best player on the floor.
那说明了很多事情
You know, that's saying a lot
当你面对的是
When you're speaking of a team
像康涅狄格大学这样的球队时
that was the caliber of connecticut.
哇！
Wow!
多漂亮的篮底动作
What a move on the runner off the glass.
我想那时候大家都认为
I think that's when everybody was like,
他不只是一个好的大学球员这么简单
"all right, he's more than just, like, a good college player.
他让一支很厉害的球队颜面尽失
Like, he just made a very good team look bad."
奥利佛·麦克纳里
后卫，哈佛大学篮球队2008-2012
凯西球被打出去，戴森抢断
Casey had it knocked away,and a steal by dyson.
林跟到篮下
Takes lin to the basket,
林在篮边给他一个盖帽！
And lin blocks him at the rim!
漂亮的盖帽
What a block.
艾默科：他拿了30分
Amaker: Scoring 30 points there,
在各方面都有贡献
Being a force to deal with in every way.
回到林手上，来到禁区，假动作，切到篮下
Back to lin top of the key, pump fake, drives
双手扣进！
And throws it down with both hands!
林书豪的漂亮扣篮！
Oh, what a dunk by jeremy lin!
他让我们一直相信
He kept us believing all the way through
我们有机会
That we have a chance.
这小子在各个方面都领导者这支球队
This guy's leading this team in every category, not just one.
丹·达根
体育作者，波士顿先驱报
他不只是个得分手
I mean, it wasn't like he was just a scorer.
他还是最好的防守队员
He was the best defensive player,
抢篮板最好，传球最好
He was the best rebounder, the best passer.
他基本上什么都最好
You know, he pretty much could do it all.
在那些时刻
It was just kind of like those moments
关键的时刻或者决定胜负的时刻
Where it was crunch time and winning time,
谁会站出来？
You know, who's gonna step up?
回到另一边，给到葛迪
Back the other way, comes to gurdy,
进入前场
Into the frontcourt.
切入到右侧
Drives down the right lane line,
右手上篮！中了！
Goes up with the right hand! Lays it in!
只剩三秒！哈佛回到另一边！
Three seconds left! Harvard back the other way!
落后一分，林书豪！
Down by a point, jeremy lin!
中场被撞倒！
Bumped at midcourt!
他被犯规，但还是投进了！
He's fouled, but got it to go!
哈佛赢了！哈佛赢了！
Harvard wins it! Harvard wins it!
难以置信！
Unbelievable!
林书豪投进了难以置信的一球
Jeremy lin on an unbelievable shot,
哈佛赢了！
And harvard has won
以最不可思议的方式！
In the most improbable fashion!
不敢相信！
I don't believe it!
我小时候
When I was growing up,
参加AAU的比赛
I was playing in the aau tournaments.
我们比赛的时候
We would play in games,
有时候，人们会说
And a couple of times, people would be like,
“哟，滚回到中国去”
"yo, take your ass back to china,"
或者说：“你就是个中国货”之类的
Or like, "you're a chinese import," or whatever.
上了大学以后，这些攻击更离谱了
When I got to college, it just, like, got crazy.
比如说：“中国佬！”
It was just like, "you chink!"
什么“你能张开眼睛吗？”
You know, "can you even open your eyes?
你看得见分数牌吗？
Can you see the scoreboard?"
这种乱七八糟的东西
You know, just like crazy stuff.
我心想：这都什么跟什么啊？
And I'd just be like, "dude, like, what is going on?"
身处目光的焦点中
Being in the spotlight
为林书豪带来不可避免的副产物
Brought jeremy an inevitable byproduct:
关注，有正面的，也有负面的
Attention, both positive and negative.
人们在看篮球运动员时
I mean, people look at basketball players in terms of...
如果用种族的角度去看
Of race a lot of times.
在美国，篮球往往被视为
Basketball is not considered
不是给亚裔玩的运动
An asian sport here in america.
我们打客场时
We'd be playing on the road,
在常春藤的某个体育馆里
Specific gyms in the ivy league,
他们会向他喊一些种族歧视的脏话
And they would yell racial slurs to him.
在常春藤联盟，看到种族歧视的辱骂
It was shocking to me to see racial taunts
让我很惊讶
In the ivy league,
到了这个级别
Because you think that at that level,
当然你会认为
Certainly in the supposed, you know,
学术氛围应该很浓厚
Very academically progressively oriented
这些校园里会有很多亚裔的学生
Group of schools full of asian students on their campuses
种族歧视的侮辱应该是不可想象的
That that would be something that was unthinkable,
但事实并非如此
But it wasn't.
我告诉他，这是一种重视的表现
I just told him, it's a sign of respect.
是，他们很无知
Yeah, they're ignorant,
但说到底
But at the end of the day,
是他们想要进入你的脑子
They're trying to get in your head.
你在想着他们说的东西
You're thinking about what they saying
而没有想着比赛
And not thinking about the game.
好像是在训练中
I think we were just working out,
我对他说
And kind of was like, you know
书豪，能跟你说句话吗？
"j, can I speak to you for a moment?"
他让我坐下
He sat me down,
4.4 助攻/场
4.4 篮板/场
16.4 分/场
总共 1,483 分
坐在体育馆外的楼梯上
Like, right outside the gym on the stairs,
他说
And he was like...
我不知道有没有人告诉过你
"I don't know if anybody's ever told you this,
但我觉得你可以去打NBA
But I think you can be an nba player."
他看着我的表情
And he kind of looked at me like, you know,
就像看到圣诞老人
He just saw santa claus or something.
我说，你疯了吧
You know, I was just like, "you're crazy," you know.
我说，兄弟，你肯定疯了
I was like, "dude, you are crazy."
我妈妈会说
My mom, you know, would be like,
你可以去打NBA
"you can make it to the nba."
呃，好吧……妈
"all right. Um, okay, mom."
这可能吗？
Is this possible?
我想也许他真的
I thought maybe he really...
有这个可能
Really have a chance.
当这个问题被提起
When the question was broached,
林书豪是不是有能力进入NBA
Is jeremy lin good enough to make the nba,
我想正是从那时开始他对这件事情产生兴趣
That's when I think a lot of the interest started surging.
能告诉我这张毯子的来历吗？
Can you tell me the history of this blanket?
这张毯子来头可大了
Oh, this blanket is legendary.
是吗？
Yeah?
上面全是《狮子王》的角色
It's all about lion king.
这里有娜娜
We have nala right here,
还有小辛巴，丁满和彭彭
Baby simba, timon and pumbaa.
这是我一直以来最喜欢的毯子
This is one of my favorite blankets of all time.
芝麻街那条毯子呢？
What about the sesame street blanket?
不，我第二喜欢的是那条加菲猫的
No. My second favorite is the garfield,
然后才到芝麻街那条
And then sesame street.
天……好吧，球迷们
oh, man. All right, fans.
晚上好，欢迎来到2010年度选秀
Good evening, and welcome to the 2010 draft
来到纽约的麦迪逊花园
At madison square garden in new york city.
第一轮，我们也没抱什么期望
The first round, we weren't expecting really much of anything.
今晚意味着
Tonight marks the realization of a dream
世界上最好的年轻球员梦想成真
For the best young players in the world.
我们都很紧张
We were just all real nervous,
因为他需要克服很多障碍
Just 'cause there were so many odds to overcome for him.
状元签，华盛顿巫师队(奇才队)
And with the first pick, the washington wizards
选择来自肯塔基大学的约翰·沃尔
Select john wall from the university of kentucky.
我确实满怀着希望，但是说实在话
I was hopeful,but to be completely honest
心里真正想的是：拭目以待到底会发生什么吧
I was like, "let's just wait and see what happens."
我一直留意着种族问题
The thing that I'm always interested in is race
联盟里种族歧视这种风气一直存在
And the way discrimination,you know, rears its ugly head.
我很好奇是否有球队会尝试冒险
I was really interested in seeing if a team would take the plunge
去选一个美籍亚裔球员
And take this asian-american player.
有意思的是
You know, it was funny.
我最有机会选上的球队
Like, the team that I had the highest chance
是尼克斯
To get drafted b was the knicks,
因为我在试训里打得特别好
cause I crushed that workout.
2010 NBA选秀大会第39顺位是
With the 39th pick in the 2010 nba draft...
我想“如果在这里我没有被选中”
I was like,"if I don'get drafted here
我很有可能就不会被任何球队选了
I probably won't get drafted."
纽约尼克斯队的选择是
The new york knicks select...
我想“天啊，如果我被选中了我该做些什么？”
I'm thinking like,"oh, if I get drafted，what's gonna happen?
我应该要围着会场跑一圈，拥抱每个人吗？
I'm just gonna run around, like，hugging everyone
明天我就要飞去纽约了
I'm gonna fly to new york tomorrow
兰德里·菲尔兹，来自斯坦福大学
Landry fields，from stanford university.
选秀结束后十分钟
10 minutesafter the draft ended,
达拉斯小牛队的经理唐尼.尼尔森
Donny nelson,the general manager
亲自打电话给林书豪
Of the dallas mavericks,personally called jeremy
让他为小牛队夏季联赛效力
And asked him to playon his summer league team.
我想大概每个落选的人
I think everyone who goes undrafted,you know,
都会有一种想要证明自己的心情，因为他们觉得自己有实力
Feels like they have to prove themselves,because they do.
因此，这对我而言确实是一个好机会
And so, you know,this is a chance
你在夏季联赛的赛场
Where you get to play against people
每晚跟选秀大会上落选的球员们一起打球
Who are drafted every single night
你要在实战中与他们竞争
And you get to compete with them in practice
而这恰好就是最好的机会
And this is the best opportunity to, you know
证明给所有的球队看
Prove to all the other teams
你是值得被选中的
That you deserved to be drafted
你本来应该得到一份合同
And you deserved to have that contract
林书豪，巧妙的进攻
Lin, surprise attack
这将是一场很有看头的比赛
Oh, this is gonna be interesting
桑德斯在防守，林成功保住这一球！
Sanders there，lin protected it home!
哇！漂亮的进球
Wow! Nice play.
我希望林书豪能成功
I hoped that jeremy would make it
因为我对他的实力有信心
Because I had confidence in his ability,
但是我疑虑的是
But I was skeptical
是否有一处可以让他真正一展身手的地方
In terms of him getting a real shot anywhere.
林书豪！
Jeremy lin!
接着在夏季联赛
And then I watched him play
我看到了他与沃尔的对决
In the summer league against john wall
我们将看到非常精彩的对位
I think we got a primetime match-up
约翰·沃尔，联盟选秀的状元
John wall, the number one overall selection
沃尔进攻！反手上篮！
Wall, creative!On the reverse.
速度够快吧？
How fast was that?
在比赛前一天我告诉林书豪
I talked to him the day before
他将跟约翰·沃尔对位
He was gonna play against john wall
这是你关键的一次表现机会
And I told him,"it's your one shot
跟沃尔对位你完全没有问题
There's no doubt that you can play against the guy."
林书豪，单手上篮！
Lin.Lin gettin' up there!
林将成为联盟里的新宠
He's gonna be an nba crowd favorite
在进攻端再次得手
Gotta work on the end.
林在右路绕过防守，在他习惯的右路上篮
Lin went right around him on his strong side
林书豪具有
The fact that he could do that
与新秀状元对位的能力，这个事实令人激动
Against the number-one player in the nba draft was tremendous
评估，建设性的意见
Assessing,constructive criticism
好球！
No way. Man!
如果你激发出他的能力，你会看到意想不到的事情
If you explode on him,you'll have something.
你会看到他身上蕴藏着无限的可能
You're gonna get your opportunity
他撕开防守，转身投篮
As he splits,spins...
太可惜了！裁判为什么要吹哨子？！
Oh, no, ref!Don't you do that!
观众们都站起来了！
They're on their feet!
天呀，这恐怕是要引起一场混战啊
Oh, my god.This is about to be a melee here
拉开他们（解说员开玩笑）
Hold 'em back,hold 'em back!
快看，观众们已经陷入疯狂了
Oh, look it, the crowd is going crazy!
他改变了一些人的狭隘眼光
He's opened some eyes
如果林不再留在小牛为夏季联赛效力
And if lin doesn't stick with the mavs
会有球队看着他的表现，心想
There are teams out there that are looking at him saying,
天呐，他完全推翻了我们的观念
"boy, he beats their system very nicely."
不管他今年是否留在夏季联赛
Whether he's in the league this year or not
都会有几支球队想要他的
He'll have some options
是的，会有几支球队想要他的
Oh, he will have some options.
我只是一心想要打球
I'm just trying to play
只要有球队有兴趣与我谈
And if someone's interested, you know,
我非常乐意去争取机会
I'd love to talk about an opportunity.
我的儿子跟林书豪都是组织后卫
Joe lacob: My son and he both were point guards
他们在AAU分属不同的球队
And they were on different aau teams
乔·拉可布
金州勇士队老板
记得在当地的体育馆
And so I remember watching them play
我看过他们的AAU比赛
These aau games in these local gyms.
当时我跟我的合伙人正好买下了勇士队
But I just happened to buy the team at that time with my partners.
我最早跟总经理说的其中一件事就是
One of the first things I told our gm was,
“我知道那个球员，我的儿子也知道他”
"look, I know this kid.My son knows this kid.”
他非常有天赋，我们应该给他一个机会“
He's really talented.We ought to give him a shot."
我想他们都觉得我有点疯了
I think they thought we were a little crazy,
但是我们还是那么做了，当你是老板
But we did, and, you know,when you're the owner,
你就有权利做些疯狂的事
You get to do things like that
勇士队球员的平均智商以及篮球智商
The warriors' iq and basketball iq
都上升了一些
Just went up a few points
因为他们签了哈佛毕业的后卫林书豪
They signed harvard guard jeremy lin
我打给林书豪告诉他我们将签下他
I called jeremy to tell him.
罗杰·蒙哥马利
林书豪的经纪人
他甚至不相信这是真的
He didn't believe me.
他说“别开玩笑了，你是认真的吗？”
He was like,"stop playing, man.Are you serious?"
我说“小伙子，这是真的”
I said,"man, it's for real
“明天就来场地练习”
"go down to the practice facility tomorrow
“然后签下合同，很好吧”
And sign the contract.It's good."
于是他说“老兄，我待会给你回电！”
And he was like,"man! I'll call you back."
你知道我几乎不敢相信“天啊”
I was like, "aah!"you know
我叫醒我弟弟
I picked my little brother up,
跟他说：金州勇士队签我了
I'm like, "I'm signing with golden state!"
我又跑到另一个房间
And I ran into the next room,
叫醒我哥哥
I picked my other brother up.
“勇士队要跟我签约了！”
"I'm signing with golden state!"
我很难描述是怎样一种心情
I can't even really describe it
因为我们兄弟从小就为NBA着迷
cause we, like, grew up,like, fantasizing about the nba
我们从小到大都支持着勇士队
And, like, the fact that we grew up rooting for the warriors
这一切使书豪进入勇士队显得更不可思议
Made it even that much crazier
作为当代的第一位美籍亚裔NBA球员
Lin has a chance to make history
林书豪很有机会创造历史
As the first asian-americannba player in the modern era
当他被勇士选中
When he got picked up by warriors
那个时刻我们想
That moment,we think
“这就是我希望他做的事情”
"this is what I want him to do."
我的梦想就是在NBA打球
My dream was to play in the nba,
现在我即将在勇士队完成我的梦想
And now I get to do it for the warriors
我是看着这支球队的比赛长大的
The team that I grew up watching
所以加入勇士队的意义比梦想成真还要深远
It's more than a dream come true
我们都知道观众为什么欢呼，林书豪上场了
We know what that's about
林书豪，曾是帕罗奥多高中的学生
Jeremy lin.Palo alto high school's own
毕业于哈佛的勇士新秀
Warrior rookie out of harvard
当时我上场的时候球馆欢呼声很大
It got pretty loud
观众们站起来为我鼓掌
And people were standing up and clapping
我环顾四周
And I just remember looking around
从小是勇士队的球迷
Grew up a warrior fan
长大后被他家乡的球队签下
Signed by his hometown team
这是一个了不起的故事
It's a great story
确实如此
It really is.
我终于来到勇士队，我终于成为勇士队的一员
It was so emotional for me to finally get there
这真的让我感慨良多
For me to finally be there
一年前我真的不敢想象我会出现在那里
And I couldn't envision myself there even a year ago.
当我看着他防守科比，我的感觉真的是（难以言喻）“哇~”
When I saw him guarding kobe,I was like, "wow."
我们从小就看科比比赛
We've been watching this guy ever since we were little
他现在……居然可以和科比同时在场上
He's actually...He's there.
没进，大卫李拿下篮板球
Missing,lee with the rebound.
我喜欢看林控球，不要犯规阻碍他
I love what lin did.Didn't foul him
啊~！
Ohh!
准备给灰熊还一记颜色
Ready to returnfor the grizzlies.Williams
林有一个空档
Lin's got an open look
结果莫名其妙把球传给了巴蒂尔
And then threw it to battier inexplicably
欢迎来到NBA
Welcome to the nba
我讨厌所有人都盯着我看
I hate when everyone's looking at me
我讨厌聚光灯
I hate the spotlight
我如何保持心态做我自己
How am I gonna be myself
每当我碰到球
When every time I touch the ball,
每个人都期待着我有疯狂的表现
Everyone's expecting me to do
期待我带来不可思议的比赛
Some crazy, miraculous play?
他得分了！
He scores!
观众们可以从我的表情看出一些端倪
People could see it on my face
譬如我在场上打球
Like, I was out there playing
但是我并没有打出自己风格
But I wasn't playing my brand of basketball
我觉得焦虑不安
I was scared, nervous
心里有很多的疑惑
And just, like,a lot of questions
巨大的压力
And a lot of stress
感觉周围有很多的不确定因素扰乱在心间
And a lot of uncertainty floating around
他缺少那么点运气
The ingredient that's missing
球队里已经有两个排在他前面的后卫了
Is the fact there was a player named monta ellis
拉里·莱利
金州勇士队
2009-2012年总经理
蒙塔埃利斯和库里
And steph curry ahead of him
在NBA水准的比赛里，教练们无疑都想赢球
You know, coaches need to win,at the nba level
当时我们队的教练基思·斯玛特
And so keith smart, who was our coach at the time,
确实没怎么让他上场
Really didn't play him a lot
事情就是这样
And this is how these things happen
一开始我告诉自己
At first, I was like,
“他知道我有实力，他知道我可以上场比赛”
"he knows I can play,he knows I can play."
可是事实是我基本上没有机会上场
And then I wasn't playing at all,
然后我看到体育新闻里写
And then I was, like,reading all these articles like,
“看吧，把他签进来只是为了多卖几件球衣”
"oh, he's just here to sell jerseys
“然后增加球队的收入”
And increase revenue."
我想：也许这就是事实
I was like,maybe that's all it is
也许这就是我在这儿起的作用
Maybe that's all I'm good for, you know
说实话我们得对自己坦诚一些
I think we have to be honest with ourselves
签林书豪进来肯定是考虑到了市场因素
There was definitely a marketing element to it
我的意思是说他是我们自己家乡人
I mean,he's a hometown guy
这里有很大比重的亚裔人口
The area has a significant asian-american population
一切都证明了确实是那样的
And the way it played out
湾区的球迷为他疯狂
You know, people went bonkers for that
在许多美国人眼里亚洲人是十分遥远和陌生的
A lot of what america perceives as asian is very foreign
姚明是一个典型的例子
Yao ming was kind of a quintessential example of that
他来自中国，他来自东方
He's from china, he's from the east
到达我们的海岸
And he's coming to our shores
但是林书豪却不同 ，他是本土产的
Whereas,jeremy is like homegrown
他是在美国本土郊外长大的亚裔小孩
He's a homegrown asian-american kid from the suburbs
跟美国其他小孩一样怀着篮球梦长大
He grew up with hoop dreams just like the rest of us
看着像林书豪这样的孩子在球场上
Seeing a kid like jeremy on the court
穿着勇士队的队服
In a warriors uniform,
这给我们很大的冲击
You know,that's a huge impact
你知道，他很开心能为自己家乡的球队效力
You know, he was happy to be playing for his hometown team
但是，我们并不满足于只是进入NBA
But we weren't satisfied with just being in the nba
球迷想看到林书豪冲到篮下
Fans want jeremy lin to go all the way to the rim
但是球却被抢走了
And he has it taken away
勇士的管理层
The warriors' management
把林书豪下放到发展联盟
Sent jeremy down to the d-league
这是NBA的小型联盟育才体系
The nba's versionof a minor league farm system
他面对着残酷的现实
He was faced with a harsh reality.
发展联盟是一道难关
The d-league is one of the toughest things
对于篮球生涯而言
When it comes to a basketball career.
发展联盟，你懂的，它是个展示的舞台
The d- league, you know, it's a showcase
人们不在乎你赢了多少场
People don't care how many wins you have.
他们只在乎你的数据
All they care about is your stats.
一切都只与你自己有关，虽然你有队友
It's all about you, and you have teammates,
但他们其实并不和你站在同一战线上
But they're not really on your team.
如果可以的话，他们会抢了你的饭碗
You know, they'll take your job if they can.
你能抢断？
You cut off?
你是控卫吗？
You the point guard?
是的
Yeah.
你把球传给我
You pass it to me...
好的
Okay.
然后你就在那儿等着
And then just wait out there.
当他去发展联盟的时候，我对他说的话很简单
What I told him when he went to the d-league was simple.
把它拿下
Go kill it.
去把发展联盟搞定，然后等着别人给我们打电话
Go and crush the d-league, and let's get called up.
因为这是一场战役
Because it's a battle, you know.
这就是一场意志上的战役
It's a battle right here.
我在想，"天啊，如果我弄砸了"
I was like, "man, like, if I play bad,
我可能就这样了
This may be it."
林书豪奋力带球
Jeremy lin drives against squeaky,
试图靠近篮架，但把球丢了
to get to the rack, throws it away!
我睡不着觉，因为我压力太大了
I couldn't really sleep, 'cause I was so stressed.
我给我哥哥打电话
I called my brother.
我说，“我现在很纠结”
I was like, "I'm trippin' right now,
我都不知道这是在干嘛
Like, I don't know what's going on."
我想，对他来说，就像是这段旅程
I think, for him, it was just like the journey
让他筋疲力尽了一样
Was kind of wearing on him.
因为这条路上的每一步
'cause, like, at every step of the way,
你都要克服所有这些障碍
You have to, like, overcome all these odds,
我认为，到了某个时间点上
And, like, I think at a certain point,
这些障碍让他感觉不可逾越
It felt insurmountable for him.
所以他那个时候状态不是很好
So he was not in a good place.
林需要稳定下来
Lin needs to settle down.
没错，他快没有力气了
Yeah, he's running out of gas.
林书豪极力地想要证明
Jeremy desperately wanted to prove
他属于NBA，但在他的新秀赛季
That he belonged, but in his rookie year,
他被3次下放到了发展联盟
He was sent to the d-league three times.
我想他被这样送来送去
I think getting sent back and forth
这种经常性来回摇摆的效应
And the constant yo-yo effect
源于被勇士队调回来
Of being taken up by the warriors,
又下放回去
Sent back down,
其积累性的结果就是给他沉重的负担
The cumulative effect of it weighed heavily on him.
你知道，我一直有那种渴望
You know, I've always had that desire,
我一直有那种渴望在我心中
And I've always had that within me
证明我能在NBA打球
Where I want to prove that I could play in the nba.
但是，你知道，我现在在这里是有原因的
But, you know, I'm here right now for a reason,
并且，你知道，神以不同的方式在起作用
And, you know, god works in very different ways.
保持住！保持住！来这儿！
Stay up! Stay up! Come here!
我觉得随着每场比赛
You know,I thought with each game,
他的自信心都在增强，并且你能看得到
His confidence grew,and you could see it
这几乎是伴随着每次场上的持球
Almost with each possession up the floor.
在他打了20场比赛的那段时间之后
And after his 20-game stint,
我觉得他走出了那段发展联盟经历的阴影
I think he came out of that d-league experience
埃里克·穆苏曼
大角羊队主教练（发展联盟）
开始相信他能在NBA中闯出名堂
Really believing that he could have an impact in the nba.
那时候很困难，因为我们知道他能打球
It was tough, because we knew he could play.
让人很沮丧的是，很多人
It was just frustrating because so many people
就只想着抛弃他，放弃他
Were so ready to just bury him and give up on him.
这对我来说很难
It's hard for me,
因为我真的很热爱篮球
Because I really love basketball.
就像是，我爱我的梦想
Like, I love my dream.
我的梦想就是打NBA
My dream is to play in the nba,
我太想实现这个梦想了，以致于我都无法想象
And I wanted it so bad that I couldn't imagine
在最后快要实现这个梦想的时候，却又马上失去了它
Finally getting it, and then losing it right away.
这里有人认为詹姆斯现在没有科比强吗？
Does anyone in here think lebron is not as good as kobe right now?
我认为詹姆斯当然没比（科比）强
I think lebron is definitely not better,
他只是更壮实
Just bigger.
好吧，这有点难讲
Well, it's kind of hard to say.
你比我们知道得更清楚，所以……
You'd know better than us, so...
不，我也不清楚
No, I don't know.
我只是坐得比你们近一些而已
I just had closer seats.
大一些的孩子们？
Older kids?
2011林书豪篮球训练营
嘿，你们来这里
Hey, you guys are in here. In here.
教练：不错，完美
Coach: Nice, perfect.
然后左边，左边，或者右边，右边。很棒
And then left, left,or a right, right. Perfect.
好，我喜欢这个
Yeah, I like that.
这里有一个很好的组
This is a good group right here!
嘿，不要动，不要动，不要动，不要动
Hey! Don't move, don't move,don't move, don't move!
就呆在那儿
Stay out there.
所有这些亚裔孩子，好像，都被我吓坏了
All these asian kidsare, like, intimidated by me.
我跟他们讲话，他们就像，”呃……“
like talk to them, they're like, "uh..."
我就说，”小兄弟，我可不是，科学怪人哦“
I'm like, "dude, I'm not, like, frankenstein."
如果对手很高的话，你就会被堵住
If they're really tall,you're gonna get stuck,
你就会被判走步
And then you'll get called for a travel.
来这里
Right here.
里奇有些话要说
Ricky has something to say.
谢谢你
Thank you.
没事，谢谢你们能来
No problem.Thanks for coming.
我记得我在发展联盟的时候，我有写日记
I remember in the d-league, I kept a little diary.
我知道这对你们来说，有点女孩子气
I know that's a little girlie to some of you guys,
但我喜欢写下我的想法
But I like to write down some of my thoughts
偶尔写一下
Every once in a while
好让我可以回顾和想起来
So I can look back and remember.
我记得在12月29号
And I remember on December 29th,
我写到，其实我多么希望
I wrote about how I actually wish
我从来没有和勇士队签约
I had never signed with the warriors.
我希望我能放弃篮球，因为我当时无法从中得到乐趣
I wish I could quit basketball, because I wasn't having fun.
让我熬过那段日子的是--
And what got me through those times--
显然，我现在没有那种感受了
Obviously, I don't feel that way now.
但当时让我熬过那段日子的也是
But what got me through that time
今天所有领导者会在这里最重要的原因
Was the number one reason why all the leaders are here today.
那就是我们想让你们知道
And that's because we want to let you guys know
神爱我，并且他有一个完美的计划给我
That god loves me and that he has a perfect plan for me,
他的计划会带你
And that his plan will take you
经历很多起起落落
Through a lot of ups and downs,
但如果我一直坚信神
But if I stay faithful to him,
最后，我知道神一定会起作用的
In the end,I know that he's gonna work
所有事情都是为了我好
Everything for my good.
现在当我打篮球的时候
Now when I play basketball,
我不再为了任何人或事去打球
I don't play for anybody else anymore.
我只为神打球
I only play for god.
这就是神给我的目的
And that's the type of purpose that he gave me,
他一旦赋予我目的性
And once he gave me that purpose,
那就是我获得内心安宁的时候
Then that's when I had my peace.
一旦我获得安宁，我就获得了喜悦
And once I got my peace, that's when I got my joy.
有时候换一种风景
Sometimes a change of scenery
可以转变对人生的看法
Can shift a perspective on life.
对我来说知道我的根是很重要的
My roots is important for me to know,
因为那就代表着我是谁
Because it's who I am.
这是我身份的很大一部分
It's a huge part of my identity.
我了解我的父母来自哪里
I understand where my parents came from,
他们是如何在那种文化里成长的
How they grew up in the culture.
哦！你把玩偶弄掉了
Oh! Oh! You dropped it!
你把它弄掉了
You dropped it!
这就是我每年回来的原因
So that's why I come back every summer
就是为了好好感受一下
Just to get a good feel for that.
我为我的身份感到骄傲
I'm very proud to be, you know, who I am.
回到农场
Back on the farm.
我现在还是退后一点吧
Oh, I'm gonna back up a little bit now.
（台语）
来看看我父亲成长的地方
Seeing where my dad grew up,
所以40年间可以发生巨大变化
So 40 years makes a huge difference,
你知道，从他在这里成长
You know, from him growing up here
到我们在美国成长
To how we grew up in the U.S.
这真的是一个很卑微的起步
It's definitely humble beginnings.
嘿，兄弟，你看到那虾了吗？
Hey, man, you see this shrimp?
哦，嘿，小心点
Oh, hey, hey. Watch yourself.
我的祖父母是在中国出生、长大的
My grandparents are born and raised in china.
我的父母在台湾出生长大
My parents are born and raised in taiwan,
我是在美国出生长大
And I was born and raised in the U.S.,
所以这里面有很多的历史
And so there's a lot of history
在我的身后有很深厚的文化
And a lot of culture behind who I am.
splendid
( A Whole New World歌词，出自动画片《阿拉丁》）
tell me, princess
now when did you last let your heart decide?
I can open your eyes
take you wonder by wonder
over, sideways, and under
on a magic carpet ride
a whole new world
你现在要去做什么？
What are you about to do right now?
我马上要出去
I'm about to go out here
去给一个扣篮大赛当评委
And judge this dunk contest.
这是最后的决赛，冠军赛
This is the finale, the championship game,
为了耐克夏季联赛
For the nike summer league,
所以我现在要去做这个了
So I'm about to get into this right now.
他们说我可以讲中文
They said I could speak chinese.
林书豪！
Jeremy lin!
这里的篮球文化很疯狂
Basketball culture here is crazy.
球迷们很热爱篮球
The fans, they love basketball.
这里总有人在打篮球
There's people playing basketball
任何时间，在任何球场上
All the time on all the courts.
这里的竞赛水平绝对在提升
The level of competition is definitely growing.
能有机会看到这些比赛
Got a chance to see some games.
所以，你知道，这真是很棒的回归
So, you know, it's definitely awesome coming back
而且还看到这项运动（篮球）在这个国家进步了这么多
And seeing how much the sport has grown in the country.
准备，预备，开始！
Ready, set, go!
我想来到这里
I just think coming here,
我看到了很多勤奋努力的人
I'm seeing a lot of really diligent, hard workers.
我感到所有人都很用功
I feel like everybody works very hard,
他们做了所有他们能做的事
And they do everything they can
就为了养活他们自己，还有他们的家人
To support themselves and their families,
对于我来说，篮球就是我养活自己和家人的方式
And for me, that way is basketball.
我认为勤奋这种精神是根深蒂固的
And I think hard work is definitely ingrained
在台湾文化里，在中国文化里
In taiwanese culture, in chinese culture.
所以，对我来说，那是一些
And so, for me, that's something
我试着去学会并且接受的东西
I try to pick up on and really embrace.
哟，兄弟，我们要出发啦
Yo, man, we gotta go.
书豪？
Jeremy?
在周五早上12点01分
At 12:01 Friday morning,
NBA停摆了所有的球员
The nba locked out its players
因为劳资双方无法在新一轮的集体谈判上达成一致
After failing to reach a new collective bargaining agreement.
停摆对很多人有巨大影响
The lockout has a very large impact on a lot of people.
目前放在谈判桌上的条件
The current offer that is on the table
不是我们所能接受的
Is not one that we can accept.
停摆可能是几个礼拜
It could be a couple weeks,
也可能是几个月
Could be a couple months.
我们已经听说
We're already hearing
这将是一个长期的停摆
This is gonna be a very long lockout.
我们将进入NBA的严冬
We're about to go into the nuclear winter of the nba.
劳资双方的工资谈判过程
The collective bargaining process
已经完全破裂
Has completely broken down.
我们都身处其中
We're all in this together.
如果这些球员不给他们
And if these players don't give them
想要的，他们是不会开工的
What they want, they're not going to play.
我不认为这个问题得到了解决
I don't think it's resolved.
我觉得这是个很糟的建议
I think it's bad advice.
我其实私下里
I actually secretly
希望这次停摆能继续
Wanted the lockout to continue,
因为这给了我额外的时间去提高
Because it gave me extra time to get better.
我们愿意继续谈判
We are willing to continue discussions
基于一个有可能性的妥协的基础上
On a potential compromise.
有一些老板
There are some owners
愿意走在这个赛季之前
Who are willing to forego the season.
我们想要打篮球
We want to play basketball.
那就是我们做的事
That's what we do,
现在，我们没有一个机会
And right now, we don't have an opportunity
去球场上做我们最擅长的事
To go out and do what we do best.
如果整个赛季都没了
If we need to lose an entire season,
那也只能这么干了
We should go ahead and do it.
我所有浸满汗水的T恤都在这了
I got all my sweaty t-shirts in here, man.
那太恶心了
That's disgusting.
所以我知道停摆时间越长
So I knew the longer the lockout went,
我就会成为越出色的球员
The better player I would become.
我们在热身
We're warming up.
我们只是在热身
We're just warming up.
就是这样，那一发很完美
Boom. That's it. That one was perfect.
感觉好吗？
Feel good?
感觉很好
Feels good.
当他成为一个更好的投手
As he gets better as a shooter,
随着时间过去，就像钱，钱，钱一样
Over time it's gonna be like money, money, money.
他只会变得越来越好
He's only gonna get better,
而且他真的非常好，难道不是吗？
And he's awfully good now, don't you think?
要进入他这个脑袋，那是另外一部分
That's the other part, getting into this cranium
让他相信自己，就像我相信他一样
To get him to believe like I believe in him.
圣诞快乐，篮球迷们
Merry christmas, basketball fans.
NBA重新开赛了
The nba is coming back.
球迷们就快得到他们梦寐以求的了
Fans are getting what they want.
老板们和球员们达成了试行性的协议
Owners and players reached a tentative agreement
终结了149天的停摆
To end the 149-day lockout.
进入到我的第二年
Going into my second year,
我没有
I'm not really, like,
去想任何让我害怕的事情
Thinking about anything I'm afraid of.
你知道，我感觉，经历了我的第一年
You know, I feel like through my first year,
至少在我眼中
At least in my own eyes,
我已经向自己证明，我能在这个水平打球
Like, I proved to myself that I can play at this level.
我想在心态上，我变得更好了
And I think mentally, I'm at a much better place
我能就这样进去，然后做我自己
Where I'm just going in, and I'm just gonna be myself
打我自己的比赛
And play my own game,
从那个立场来看，我真的一点也不畏惧
And from that standpoint, I'm really not afraid
在进入训练营后发生的事情
Of anything going into training camp.
我感觉我已经没有什么可以失去了
I feel like I have nothing to lose.
我们缺一个感到满意的中锋
We didn't have a center that we felt good about,
我们需要足够的薪水空间
And we needed to create enough salary cap space
去招揽一个中锋
To go make an offer,
为了这样做，我们要裁掉一些球员
And in order to do so, we had to cut somebody.
这是我们做过的决定中
It was one of the hardest decisions
最艰难的决定之一
That we could have had to make.
他们中途给我打电话
They called me upmidway through
在训练的中途
In the middle of a drill.
他们说，“嘿，你需要到楼上来一趟”
They're like, "hey, you got to go upstairs."
我走到楼上，然后总经理
I went in there, and the general manager
和助理总经理说，
And assistant general managerwere like,
“我们得裁掉你”
"we gotta let you go.
“我们想要德安德鲁·乔丹”
We're trying to get deandre jordan."
他已经在赛季前付出了巨大的努力
He had worked tremendously hard pre-season,
所以我想，“天啊，这是一个大打击啊”
o I was like, "man, this is a blow.
我的意思是，这就像一脚，刚好踢在你的肚子上
I mean, this is a kick in the stomach right here."
他们就像
They were like,
“哦，我们祝你好运”
"oh, we wish you the best of luck."
我说，“谢谢”
I was like, "thanks."
48小时后
Within 48 hours,
他被休斯敦火箭队接收
He was picked up by the houston rockets.
是的，我们一直在希望
Yeah, we were hoping
没有其他队把他挑走
That no one else picked him up.
我们对他感兴趣，已经有很长一段时间了
We were interested in him for quite a long time.
看过他在哈佛的比赛
Had been to his games at harvard.
那时候，我们就把他招进来，然后说
At the time, we just added him and said,
“嘿，让他加入看看会发生什么”
"hey, let's bring him in and see what happens."
我就去了休斯敦
I went to houston.
当时那里有6个控卫
There were six point guards there.
我甚至没法参加训练
I couldn't even get reps in practice.
我不明白
I don't understand.
我在金州勇士队是个候补控卫
I was backup point guard at golden state,
现在他们把我带到这里
And now they're gonna bring me here,
然后我成了第六根弦（吉他声音最低的那根弦）？
And I'm sixth string?
林书豪在带球
Jeremy lin on the drive.
把球带到篮筐，然后上篮
Take it to the rim, lays it up.
在马刺队大个子球员面前的一个好球
Good shot with the spurs' bigs right in his face.
当火箭队接收了他
When the rockets picked him up,
对于他来说，可能已经是跌入瓶底了
That was probably the bottom of the barrel for him.
一个周日晚上，我们在联谊会上
Sunday night, we were in fellowship,
我记得林书豪说，“嘿，我得走了”
And I remember Jeremy said, "hey, I gotta go.
“我得赶飞机去休斯顿“
"I gotta catch my flight to Houston."
他当时站在门口
He was standing at the door,
他眼中含泪，因为……
And he had tears in his eyes, because, um...
因为压力真的让他难以承受
Because the pressure was really getting to him.
他不知道他的未来里还有什么
He just didn't know what his future was gonna hold.
我记得他转向我，然后说
And I remember he turned to me and he says,
“我不知道我还能不能继续撑下去”
"I don't know if I can keep doing this."
仅仅在火箭队待了12天
After only 12 days with the rockets,
他再一次被裁
He was cut again.
那天正好是圣诞节
It was christmas day.
过去几周显然发生了很多事情
So obviously a lot has been happening the last couple of weeks.
你心里在想什么？
What's going through your mind,
你今天感觉怎么样？
And how you feeling today?
圣诞节早上，我被裁了
Christmas morning, I was waived.
圣诞夜，我坐飞机回家
Flew back home on christmas night,
两周之内，我两次被裁
And within two weeks, I had been waived twice
而裁掉我的两个队说他们还需要我
By two teams who said they still wanted me.
今天早上10点
10 a.M. This morning,
我得知纽约尼克斯队选了我
Um, found out the knicks had picked me up.
马上我将第一次为尼克斯队上场
And that's gonna be my first game with the knicks.
在甲骨文球馆（金州勇士队主场，林书豪待的第一支NBA球队）
It's gonna be at oracle arena.
这场比赛明天晚上就要打了
You know, I'm literally going into this game tomorrow night,
而我还完全不知道队友有哪些人
I have no idea who my teammates are.
我从未和他们一起打过球
I've never played with them one time.
我完全不知道我们执行什么战术
I have no idea what plays we run.
球队的一个战术也不清楚
I don't know a single play,
甚至还没和教练讲过话
And, you know, I haven't even talked to the coach yet,
所以这下“好玩”了
So it's gonna be interesting.
林书豪要上场了
I see jeremy lin coming in.
他们（尼克斯）今天刚刚签下他
They just signed him today.
只是在赛前的投篮练习稍微活动了一下
Went through a walk-through, at shoot-around today.
林去年在金州勇士队打过寥寥几场比赛
Lin, who played with golden state last year sparingly,
在发展联盟也打过
Played in the d-league,
欢呼很热烈
Gets a nice ovation.
这是我绝好的机会
It's a great opportunity for me
只要能打上球
To be able to just play,
现在对我来说
And I think, for me right now,
最重要的一件事
The one thing I really care about
就是这样一个打球的机会
Is just an opportunity to play.
我将倾尽全力
I'm gonna give my best effort,
就算最终失败
And, you know, if I go down,
我也要用我的方式证明自己
I'm gonna make sure I go down doing it my way,
同时，也是神的方式
Which is god's way.
所以比赛前一晚
So it's the night before,
我打包好了行李
And, you know, I gotta get my bags ready,
明天的比赛过后，我们将前往洛杉矶
And after the game tomorrow, we head to l.A.,
再来是萨克拉门托，然后将飞去纽约，一直待在那里
Sacramento, and then I'm off to new york for good.
五场比赛过去了，我却一分钟都没上
Five games go by, and I'm not playing at all.
我觉得这一切都说不通
Nothing was really making sense to me.
如果你签了我
If you bring me in,
却连球队训练也不让我打
And you don't let me play in practice,
更不要说正式比赛了，那为什么要我呢？
Let alone the games, then why am I here?
我当时觉得，我可以帮助你们
I felt like, you know, I could help you,
而只能眼睁睁地看着球队输球
And I was watching us lose.
尼克斯队已经四连败了
The knicks have lost four straight games.
连败还在继续
And the losing streak continues.
尼克斯队已经六连败了
Knicks have now lost six in a row.
尼克斯队的场上没有很好的化学反应
There's a chemistry problem there on the floor.
他们需要一个控卫来分配球
They need a point guard to distribute the ball.
林书豪最初的两年合同
Jeremy's original two-year contract
即将到期
Was about to expire,
这意味着如果尼克斯队裁掉他
Which meant that, if the knicks let him go,
他不仅得不到薪水，而且，将永远失去机会
He'd be dropped with no pay, and, this time, for good.
在训练时，书豪站在我旁边
During practice, jeremy was standing right beside me
麦克·德安东尼
尼克斯2008-2012主教练
就站在场边
On the side of the court
但没有加入训练
And not really get in even in practice.
我们把他签下来只是
以防万一哪天有人受伤时顶替的
He was just there in case one of these guys got hurt.
我已经隐约有预感了
I pretty much saw the writing on the wall.
当时就想，“差不多就是这样了”
I was like, "I'm pretty much done,"
我只能接受现实
And, like, I was resigned to the fact
我又要被裁了
That I was gonna get let go.
站在场边的时候，他走向我
Standing on the side of the court, he comes up to me,
他说，“嘿，教练，我有一个问题。”
And he goes, "hey, coach, I've got a question."
我就说，“书豪，什么问题？”
I go, "what is it, jeremy?"
“我在这儿一直都是打出租车的”
"I'm taking a taxi everywhere.
“我应该把我的车带过来吗？”
Should I ship my car out here?"
当时他的反应是，“呃，也许不必”
And he was like, "uh, you know, probably not."
我当时就想，“完了，又要被裁了“
I was like, "oh, hell, I'm gonna get waived."
所以我就跟助教格兰说
And so I went and talked to glen.
我说，“格兰，你怎么看？”
I said, "glen, what do you think?"
他说，“其实我们还没有真正看过他打球”
And he goes, "well, we haven't really seen him.
“我们不清楚”
We don't know."
我说，“这样吧，我们就让他试试”
And I said, "you know what? Let me try to see
“如果周二之前让他试着打几场比赛”
"if we can get him in a couple games
“看看会发生什么”
Before Tuesday and just see what happens."
他们对我说，“今晚你要上场”
They're like, "look, you're gonna play tonight.
“上场之后”
"I want you to go out there.
“不希望你做太多事情”
I don't want you to do too much."
我说，“好的，我不会的”
I was like, "okay, I won't."
加内特已经得了8分
8 points for garnett.
林书豪丢球，布拉德利断球上篮得分
Lin coughs it up, bradley to the rim.
我真的没有做很多事
I didn't do too much.
我几乎什么都没做，我的表现糟透了
I pretty much did nothing, and I played horrible.
投篮不中
You know, I missed shots,
又是失误，又是犯规
I had turnovers, I had bad fouls.
林书豪犯规
Lin reached in.
我想，我最多还有一次机会
I thought, at most,
就是下一场比赛
I had one more chance the next game.
我当时想，我刚刚搞砸了和波士顿的比赛
I was like, "okay, I just screwed the boston game.
“也许我要被裁了”
"I probably will get cut,
“但他们明天可能会再给我一次机会”
But they may give me one more chance tomorrow."
我记得那时
I think at the time,
书豪其实住在他纽约的哥哥那
Jeremy was actually staying with his brother in new york,
而在飞机上他跟我说
And he was talking to me on the plane.
兰德里·菲尔兹
后卫，尼克斯2010-2012
今晚会有一些朋友在我哥那过夜
He's like, "you know, my brother, he's got some people over,
所以，我可不可以
"um, so, you know, is it cool
在你家睡一晚上？
If I crash at your place instead?"
我说，“当然可以”
You know, I was like, "yeah, sure, man, you can come."
不过我也有提醒他
I was giving him forewarning, though,
我的沙发不太大
That my couch wasn't huge.
那个沙发是租来的
It was actually a rental couch at the time.
差不多只有六英尺（183厘米）长
It might have been maybe six feet long.
我们大概凌晨2点才到
We get in at, like, 2:00 in the morning.
我去了菲尔兹家
I go over to landry's place.
他给我看了他的沙发
He's like, "this is my couch,"
大概这么大
And his couch is like this big.
我当时就无语了
I'm like, "dude."
我只能把头挂在沙发一头
I have my head hanging off of one end
双脚挂在另外一头
And my legs hanging off the other.
这样怎么能睡得好呢？
I'm like, "oh, my gosh, how am I gonna get a good night's rest?"
明天还要打球
Like, "I might play tomorrow.
这也许是我最后的机会
This might be my last chance."
我记得当时对自己说
I remember thinking to myself,
第一，我希望他能上场
One, I hope he gets in,
因为他在波士顿的糟糕表现
Because he really didn't do enough in the boston game
无法保证他有足够的上场时间
To warrant getting big minutes.
第二，如果他上场，他必须有好的表现
And, two, if he gets in, he's gotta play well,
不然这场比赛过后他们就会裁了他
Or they're gonna release him after the game.
有趣的是
It's funny.
本赛季是上次停摆后11、12年内
This season was the only season in the
last, like, 11, 12 years since the last lockout
唯一有连着三场背靠背的赛季
where people have played back-to-back-to-back games.
而尼克斯队只有一次连着三场背靠背
And new york only had one stretch of back-to-back-to-back games.
如果当时有更多休息时间
And if we had more days to rest,
我不确定那场比赛我能否上场
I'm not sure if I would have been able to play in that game.
那天我祷告了
I prayed that day,
我的祷告是
And my prayer is,
“神啊，如果让他打NBA是你的意愿”
"god, if this is your will for him to play nba,
“那么你需要展现给他看”
You need to show it."
莫罗再次得分
There's morrow. Morrow knocks it down.
德隆投篮
Williams sets himself,
三分命中
Puts up the 3, and knocks that one down.
尼克斯队已经落后10分了
The knicks find themselves down by 10 already.
尼克斯队的山姆波特，个人第二次犯规
New york foul is on shumpert, his second.
看看谁要上场了
Again, mike, look who's coming in.
是林书豪，你可以听到球迷的大声欢呼
Jeremy lin, and you hear a pretty big ovation.
他看起来没有犹豫
He didn't look tentative,
也没有过于忧虑
He didn't look overly concerned.
他看起来就像在说，“我要放手一搏了”
He looked like, "dude, I'm about to go do it.
如果他们裁了我就裁吧
"if they cut me, they cut me.
就算我再也不能在NBA打球也无所谓了
"if I don't never play another nba game, so be it.
我要让你们看看真正的林书豪是怎么打球的
I'm going to play like jeremy lin can play."
林书豪突破上篮
Jeremy lin drives and finishes.
漂亮的上篮得分
Nice play from lin.
丢球了
There's a strip of it.
林书豪长传给道格拉斯
Lin throws it ahead to toney douglas.
擦板得分
Up for the layup! Banks it in!
山姆波特杀过来了，传球给林
Here comes shumpert to lin.
林上篮，球进了
Lin flips it up and puts it in.
又是林书豪！
Jeremy lin once again!
他的半场数据差不多是10+4+4
He finished the half with like 10, 4, and 4,
对半场来说很不错了
Like, good numbers for a half.
超过了他之前所做的一切
That was such a higher high than, like, anything he's, like, done.
我当时欣喜若狂
So I was, like, ecstatic at that point.
而到了下半场，他简直
The second half, he just went...
简直疯了
He just went nuts.
（林书豪）突到篮下了，球又进了
Driving to the basket, does it again.
同时有加罚的机会
He's got a chance for a 3-point play as he got hit.
（林书豪）撞到佩特洛，又杀向篮筐了
Bumped by petro, gets to the rim.
进球有效，还造成对手犯规
Count it and a foul!
林书豪！
Jeremy lin!
他经历了美妙的一晚
He has in one special night
成了（麦迪逊广场）花园的宠儿
Become a garden favorite.
今晚会被人记住吗？
Will it be remembered?
他连着做了
He was stringing together,
三个胯下运球
Like, three crossover moves in a row.
过去他从未这样做过
Like, things he's never done before.
（林书豪）再次撕开防守
Splits the defense again!
杀到篮下了！上篮命中！
Gets to the rim! Pops it in!
还造成犯规！哇！
And a foul! Wow!
球迷已经都坐不住了
And the crowd on their feet
站起来向这个男人致敬
Paying homage to this man.
看起来连他的队友们
Clyde, even it looks like his teammates
也不相信所发生的一切
Don't believe what they're seeing.
我当时太兴奋了
I was just so emotional.
现在他们不能把我裁掉了
There's no way they can cut me now.
我刚刚打了生命中最重要的比赛
I just had the game of my life.
又是一个胯下运球后杀向篮筐
Again, the crossover, the basket.
投篮，又进了
Puts it up, pops it in!
林书豪，25分！
Jeremy lin with 25!
球迷们已经疯狂了！
And this crowd is going crazy!
尽情地突破，玩弄
Penetrating, manipulating,
完全摧毁了篮网队
Devastating the nets!
他是来自哈佛的英雄
He's the hero from harvard,
尼克斯队终于
As the knicks
拿到了一场亟需的胜利，这是他生命中最重要的比赛
Get a much-needed victory on the game of his life.
他已经被兴奋的队友包围
And he is swarmed by his ecstatic teammates
还有麦迪逊广场花园兴奋的球迷
And a jubilant crowd here at madison square garden.
感谢神
I'm just thankful to god
赐予我这次上场的机会
For this opportunity to be able to come out here
来为这支球队打球
And play with this team and this organization.
我洗了个澡
Man, I was taking a shower,
我甚至分不清
And I was like... I didn't even know.
那是洗澡水
I was like, "is this water, like, from the shower,
还是我流下的喜悦的泪水
Or am I actually crying, like, tears of joy?"
我实在是太兴奋了
Oh, I was just, like, so high on emotion.
我太开心了，我就坐在浴室里
I was so happy. I was sitting in the shower,
脑子里在回放发展联盟里的那些时光
Replaying all the times in the d-league,
那些我不得不经历的
All these flashbacks of these tough times
艰苦岁月的片断
I had to go through.
我记得我出来后
And I remember I got out,
看到我的家人，他们都在微笑
I saw my family, and they were all smiling.
我打电话给经纪人
I called my agent,
他在对我大喊大叫
And he was yelling at me on the phone, you know, like,
他说，“我太为你骄傲了！我就知道你行的”
"I'm so proud of you. I knew you could do it."
这就是我希望取得的突破
That was kind of like the much-needed breakthrough that I was hoping for.
在林书豪取得对篮网队的惊艳表现之前
Before jeremy lin's first big game against new jersey,
他根本不在尼克斯队的计划之内
He really wasn't in the knicks' plans at that point,
据我所知
And I'm told they had begun
他们当时已经考虑换掉他了
To look seriously at replacements.
周六晚上的麦迪逊广场花园
Clyde, Saturday night, madison square garden
和整个赛季一样人声鼎沸
Sounded as loud as we've heard it all season.
他无与伦比
He was magnificent.
从尼克斯队的角度
You just hope from a knicks standpoint
你会希望他能引领进攻
That he can run the offense
保持周六那样的精彩表现
As well as he ran it on Saturday.
第一次首发我其实没有特别紧张
I just really wasn't nervous for my first start.
通常来说，我应该会紧张
And, you know, usually, I would be,
但不知道为什么我感觉很舒服
But I don't know why I just felt really comfortable,
超出自然的平静
And it was just a supernatural peace,
这就是一些我无法解释的事情
And it's one of those things that, you know, I can't really explain.
林书豪的第一次NBA首发出场
For jeremy's first nba start,
阿玛尔·斯塔德迈尔因个人原因缺阵
Amar'e stoudemire was out for personal reasons,
卡梅隆·安东尼上半场因伤下场
And carmelo anthony suffered an injury in the first half.
安东尼走路很艰难
Carmelo anthony comes up hobbling.
他很难受
He's in a lot of discomfort.
他现在已经不能走路了
He can't move right now.
尼克斯队现在需要一位领袖
The knicks desperately needed a leader,
而林书豪将承担起这个使命
And jeremy would answer the call.
林书豪绕过杰弗森
Lin gets around jefferson,
还在看人，上反篮得分
Looking, and backs it in.
上场比赛有不少这样的表现
He had a couple of those the other night.
我们不断地打挡拆
We were running pick and roll
一个挡拆接一个挡拆
After pick and roll after pick and roll.
林书豪传给里面的杰弗里斯
Lin inside to jeffries!
我不知道他能否保持对篮网那场的表现
I didn't know how he would follow up, that new jersey game,
因为那场实在太棒了
'Cause it was such a high,
但是（本场比赛）他不断上演各种夸张的上篮
But he just kept making ridiculous layups,
各种跳投命中
He was hitting jumpers.
他们不了解我的打球习惯
They didn't know my tendencies,
他们不知道我的弱点
They didn't know my weak spots,
也不知道我的优势和最佳投篮点
My strong spots, my sweet spots.
林书豪突进来了
Lin on the drive,
拉杆，命中！
Flips it up, drops it in!
同时造成犯规！好一个反手上篮！
And a foul! Reverse layup!
他们从未看过我打球
They had never seen me play.
向前推进，传给山姆波特，又回传给林书豪
Pushing it, ahead to shumpert, back to lin.
林被打到了，球还是放进，2+1！
Lin gets hit, puts it in, and a foul!
上篮
Lays it up, puts it up,
还是活球
Chandler keeps it alive.
林必须得投了
lin has to put it up.
在进攻24秒结束前三分命中
A 3-pointer as the shot clock expired!
我像压榨秘书似的使用他
I'm riding him like friggin' secretariat.
林书豪
Jeremy lin
连续两个职业生涯的重要夜晚
With his second consecutive career night.
他现在是尼克斯队新的首发控卫
He is the new starting point guard of the knicks.
尼克斯队再次取胜
And the knicks win again.
全场观众起立向林书豪致敬
A standing ovation for jeremy lin.
过程中有非常多细微的因素
You know, there's so many little variables
是我无法掌控的
With every step of the way being something I can't control.
比如，休斯顿火箭队晚了一天才裁掉我
You know, houston waives me a day late.
如果他们早一天裁掉我
If they waive me a day earlier,
就会超过裁人的线
I would have been past the waiver wire.
那天早上山姆波特正好受伤
Shumpert gets hurt that morning.
尼克斯队才选了我
The knicks pick me up,
因为去年他们试训过我
Because they had worked me out the year before.
正好，尼克斯队的主教练是德安东尼
You know, it happens to be d'antoni who's coaching here
他的进攻体系就像是为我量身打造的
Whose offense is tailor-made for me.
突然之间，一切都变得疯狂了
And all of a sudden, things just go crazy.
过去两场他平均得分26.5分
He's averaging 26 1/2 points a game the last two games.
我认为这不可持续
I don't think that's gonna continue.
这显然无法持续
Obviously, that's not gonna continue.
接着我们踏上客场之旅，前往华盛顿
Then we hit the road and go to washington,
又将遇上约翰·沃尔
And it's like john wall again, you know.
夏季联赛的时候我和沃尔交过手
Like, I played against john wall in the summer league,
现在狭路相逢
And now it's, like, a rematch.
又要和他对位
Now I'm playing against him again.
呜~
Ooh!
林书豪突破到禁区内
Lin on the drive, gets inside.
林书豪反手上篮，漂亮！
Reverse layup. Great play by jeremy lin.
沃尔杀过来了，看着
Here comes wall. Look at wall.
撕开防守
Breaks the press,
左手暴扣
And throws it down with the left hand!
我当时的反应是，靠，他居然在我头上扣篮
I was like, "dang, he kinda dunked on my head."
我必须还以颜色！
I was like, "I'm gonna try to get him back."
几个回合过后，他们的防守出了问题
Couple possessions later, they messed up their coverage,
我轻松地突进去
I had a free lane,
就试着去扣扣篮
And I just tried to take the rim down.
林书豪突破！
Lin drives!
这才是你说的扣篮
There's the dunk you're talking about, clyde.
林书豪点燃球迷的激情
Jeremy lin fires up the crowd.
我看到这么大的空当
When I saw that opening,
我只是用尽全力去完成那记扣篮
I just tried to dunk it as hard as I could.
我不知道
I don't know. There's just...
只是有太多的痛苦和磨炼
There's been so much pain and so many trying times,
现在终于能打上球了
And now that I get to play,
我只是想把这些都宣泄出来
I'm just letting it all out, man.
把一切都宣泄在球场上
I'm just letting it all out on the floor.
比赛过后，当我回想时
After the game, I just look back,
觉得很有趣
And I'm like, "man, that was so fun."
一个美妙的故事正在酝酿，主角是林书豪
The great story that's brewing is jeremy lin,
他本年度的合同算是有保证了
And this week, contracts are guaranteed for the rest of the year.
他的球场表现就像在说，“让他的价值充分展现”
（电影《甜心先生》的台词）
He's been balling out, saying, "show that man his money."
有一点可以肯定，他在场上的视野很好
The things that's for real is his vision,
这不会变
Which won't change,
他的速度不会变
His speed, which won't change,
他对比赛的认知不会变
His knowledge of the game, which won't change.
我就是觉得不会变
I just don't see it changing.
请不要再引用我的话了
Now, again, please don't quote me on that one.
肯尼·史密斯：现在他该出现在球探报告里了
Kenny Smith: Now he's on the scouting report.
沙奎尔·奥尼尔： 是的，当然
Shaquille o'neal: Yeah, he is now.
我们来看看他是否在洛杉矶湖人队的球探报告里
Let's see if he's in the scouting report for the lakers
没错，周五晚上，关注麦迪逊广场花园
Oh, yeah, he is. On Friday night at the garden.
过去两周我就是睡这里的
This is basically where I lived the last two weeks
睡在这张沙发上
And so it's the couch I slept on.
我的哥哥和大嫂
Uh, my brother and sister-in-law,
好好地招待了我
Uh, did a good job of hosting me.
很开心
Had a lot of fun.
现在他们的小弟弟就要搬出去了
And now their little kid might have to move out.
如果我现在不洗衣服
If I don't do laundry now,
那我结婚了也不会洗，没错
I won't do laundry when I'm married. Fact.
大嫂：你们脏死了
Sister-in-law:You guys are brats.
我们会做别的事情
So? We do other things.
大嫂：比如？
Sister-in-law: Like what?
什么比如不比如的
What do you mean, like what?
你应该问有什么是我们不做的
Like, what don't we do, is the question.
大嫂：那你会做什么？
Sister-in-law: What do you do?
妈妈： 你 会做什么？
Shirley: What do you do?
我每天都午睡
I take a nap every day.
妈妈：是的，这个我了解
Shirley: Yeah, that I know.
没有很多人能做到这个
Who does that? Not many people can.
没有很多人可以
Not many people can.
你还是个吃货
And you eat a lot,
一天到晚吃个不停
Nonstop all day long. Yeah.
昨天，总经理跟我说
Yesterday, the general manager was like,
书豪，你的合同有保障了
"hey, jeremy, by the way, you're guaranteed now,
不要睡沙发了
So get off the couch."
我......
I was like...
妈妈：他其实有地方住
Shirley: This guy has a place to stay,
但是他不想住那
But he doesn't want to stay there.
只想赖在这里
He want to crash in here.
他们可不想这个上新闻
They don't want this to be on the news,
林书豪睡在他哥哥的沙发上
Jeremy sleeping on the couch at his brother's.
为什么？
Why?
这太疯狂了
It's crazy.
太疯狂了
It's just crazy to...
告诉你吧，我的社交网络，我的手机
I'm telling you, social media, Twitter, facebook, my phone, it's just...
我不知道还能不能更疯狂
I don't know if it could get crazier than this.
我真的不知道
Like, I really don't.
林书豪？
Jeremy lin?
有听说过吗？
Are you following that story at all?
不知道，听过一下
No idea. I know who he is,
但我真的不太清楚状况
But I don't really know what's going on too much with that.
你对林书豪过去一周的表现感到震惊吗？
Are you surprised at the production that lin's had over the past week?
我还不知道他做过什么
I don't even know what he's done.
根本就不知道你们说的是哪个人
Like, I have no idea which you guys are talking about.
我看了一些报道
I'm reading all these quotes
关于他（科比）说了什么
About what he's saying.
“科比完全不知道林书豪是何人”
"kobe bryant has no idea who jeremy lin is."
我的反应是，“什么”？
I'm like, "what?"
我在想，“你为什么要这么说”
I'm like, "why would you do that?
“我完全没有谈论你”
"I didn't say anything about you.
“从没说过你的坏话”
I never talked bad about you."
所以听说这件事时，我心想……
So when I heard that, I was like...
“球场上见”
"here we go."
你会单防他吗？
Would you consider guarding him
如果他的表现很好？
If he's having one of those games?
你们不要着急
Let's not get ahead of ourselves here.
加油！
Let's go!
新的英雄已经出现
There is a new man in town.
狭路相逢勇者胜
"may the best man lin(win)."
今晚的竞猜，林书豪能否超过23分
Over-under, 23 points for lin tonight, bomani.
对手是内线长人如林的湖人队
Against the lakers with those trees they've got inside?
今晚不会有那么多林疯狂时刻了
It won't be so linsane tonight.
今晚谁得分高？科比还是林书豪？
Kobe or lin? Who scores more tonight?
我选林书豪，我的英雄
I'm going with my guy, jeremy lin, my hero.
因为他无所不“林”
Because all he does is lin, baby!
短短一周
Jeremy lin in just one week
林书豪就改变了一切
Has turned things around
无论对他自己还是尼克斯队来说
For his career and for the new york knicks.
我爱林书豪，太棒了！
I love it! It's awesome, man!
这是纽约发生过最美妙的事情
This is like the greatest thing that's happened to new york ever.
就是这么一个夜晚
It's one of those nights,
一个故事
And it's one of those stories
让我们知道为何如此热爱体育
Where it really is why we love sports.
我不知道结果会怎样
I didn't know how it was gonna turn out,
但是
But I was like,
我将非常非常具有攻击性
"I'm just gonna be really, really aggressive."
我们的比赛进行得很顺利，投篮都弹无虚发
Everything was going well, everything was going down.
林书豪跳投，命中！
Lin puts it up, puts it in!
完美的开局
Terrific start!
听听球迷的欢呼吧！
And listen to this garden crowd.
我记最让我激动不已的是
I think the one thing where I kind of lost it a little bit,
看着他带球，突然急停转身
He'd come down, he kind of like stutter-stepped, and spun
手指很柔软地轻轻一投
And finger-rolled it.
林喜欢这个大空当
Lin likes the open floor.
转身，投篮，命中！
Spinning, puts it up and puts it in!
林书豪，超级精彩的得分
Sensational play for jeremy lin!
整个球馆都沸腾了，在这样一个全国瞩目的舞台
The garden erupted, and to do it on the national stage,
任何人看过之后都永生难忘
Anybody who saw that moment will never forget.
又一次点燃了麦迪逊广场花园
Electrifying the garden again!
他已经得了18分了
He's got 18 points.
欢迎来到演播室，这是林书豪的半场个人表演
Welcome to our studios for the jeremy lin toyota halftime show.
林书豪是顶级的
Jeremy lin was superb,
投篮12中7
7 of 12 from the field,
拿下18分5次助攻
18 points, 5 assists.
科比和他的队友的投篮手感还很差
Kobe bryant and the lakers struggling shooting the ball,
但现在他们还只落后8分
But they're only down by 8.
科比，一系列假动作
Bryant, a couple of fakes,
要投篮了，球进了
Gonna put it up, and knocks it down.
林书豪抢断
Stripped by lin, stolen by lin.
助攻左侧的山姆波特，左手上篮命中！
Left side, shumpert, left-handed layup!
科比转身，高难度的一球
Bryant spinning, difficult shot.
又是科比
Kobe bryant again.
他要开始接管比赛了
He is starting to get in one of those zones right now.
加索尔在防守林书豪
Gasol is on lin.
一个两分球，进了！
Puts up the 2-pointer. Puts it in!
林书豪31分！
Jeremy lin with 31!
杰弗里斯抢下篮板
And the rebound by jeffries.
林书豪三分
Lin for 3.
梆！
Bang!
三分命中
3-pointer!
林书豪！
Jeremy lin!
我整年最喜欢的一次得分
And my favorite play of this whole year
就是那个底脚的三分
Was when I hit that 3 in the corner
因为那场比赛有太多的渲染
Just because that game had so much hype,
那记投篮就像一把匕首
And that shot was kind of the dagger
狠狠地给了他们一刀
That put the game out of reach for them.
本赛季两次被裁
Already cut twice this season,
因为无处可去而只能睡在队友的沙发上
Sleeping on a teammate's couch, because he had nowhere else to go,
而一夜之间，他成了曼哈顿的宠儿
And, suddenly, jeremy lin is the toast of manhattan.
就在这里
This is it right here.
这就是我的梦想
This is my dream, and, uh,
我感谢神
I'm just thankful to god, man,
让我美梦成真
Because this is my dream being lived out,
我无比感恩
And I'm so thankful for that.
林书豪38分
Jeremy lin, 38 points.
本赛季尼克斯队球员的得分新高
It's the most by a knick this season.
“林疯狂”还在麦迪逊广场花园继续
Linsanity continues here in madison square garden.
这真的难以形容
It's indescribable, really.
我从未见过这样的事情
It's something I've never seen before.
我没有预料到
I didn't foresee this coming.
难以置信
You know, it's unbelievable.
我这人会很奇怪
This is, like, how weird I am.
我当时想这场比赛之后我要出口气
I was like, "I'm gonna go off this game,"
采访结束时，他们肯定会问我
And at the end of the interview, they're gonna be like,
你觉得科比现在认识你了吗？
"oh, so do you think kobe knows who you are now?"
书豪，你知道肯定有个人会问你这个问题
Jeremy, you knew somebody was gonna ask you this,
你认为科比现在认识你了吗？
But do you think kobe knows who you are now?
如果他们问我那个问题
If they ask me that question,
我的回答会是，“科比？谁啊？”
I'm gonna be like, "who the hell is kobe?"
我本想这样回答
That's what I was gonna say.
但我想了一会儿
And then I, like, thought about it,
祷告的时候
And I prayed about it,
想想神会怎么做呢？
I was like, you know, "what would jesus do?"
不，神应该不会这么说
And I'm like, "jesus probably wouldn't say that,"
所以我要改变我的答案
So I was like, "I'm gonna change my answer."
“这得问科比本人了”
Aw, well, you guys have to ask kobe.
我不知道
I don't know.
让我们来看看当今体育界最大的新闻：林书豪
Let's get to what matters in sports today, jeremy lin.
林书豪现在是纽约的第一巨星
Right now, the biggest star in new york is jeremy lin.
就算你不关注体育也一定听过他的故事
I don't even think you have to
be a sports fan to hear about this story.
“林旋风”横扫纽约全城
New york has a raging case of linsanity.
现在是疯狂的时刻
That's what it is right now. It's madness right now.
林书豪
Jeremy lin!
无所不“林”
All I do is lin, lin, lin.
你觉得怎么样？
What do you think?
你觉得现在的一切如何？
What do you think about all this?
疯狂，太疯狂了
Um, it's crazy. It's just crazy.
现在体育界最大的头条
One of the biggest headlines
就是“林疯狂”
In sports right now is linsanity.
你还没听说过他？你会的
If you haven't caught it yet, you will.
“林疯狂”席卷纽约城
Linsanity takes new york by storm.
他实在是尼克斯队没有办法的办法了
He was a last-ditch effort for the knicks.
当时的情况可能是，有人说，“今晚谁想上场吗？”
They sort of said, "all right, who wants to play?"
他举起了手，然后就有人说，“那好，你上吧”
And he raised his hand and, "all right, get in there."
我这么多年报道体育以来前所未闻的事情
I have never seen anything like this in all my years of covering sports.
从为见过一个人从默默无闻
I've never seen somebody go from a no-name
在两周之内成为一个轰动的现象
To an absolute phenomenon inside of two weeks.
太难以置信了
It's unbelievable.
他有魅力、有型、有天赋
He's doing it with charisma, with style, with flair,
而且，他还打得很开心
And he's having fun.
这很疯狂，火得不行
It's crazy. It's catching fire.
我觉得“林疯狂”这个词
Linsanity, I think it'll probably be
将会收录到下一版的字典里
In the dictionary in the next version.
林疯狂？我爱林疯狂
Linsanity? I love it.
我爱林疯狂，我为他感到高兴
I love linsanity. I'm so happy for him.
林书豪（过去三场）得了89分
Jeremy lin's 89 points,
这是所有球员自NBA和ABA合并以来
职业生涯前三场首发合计最高分
The most by any player in his first
three pro starts since the aba-nba merger.
传给外面的林，林面对里德诺胯下运球
Outside to lin, crosses over ridnour,
投篮命中
And hits.
林书豪空中连线菲尔兹
Jeremy lin up top to fields.
林迅速杀到篮下
Lin a whirling dervish right to the rim,
左右腾挪完成上篮
Zigzagging to the cup.
尼克斯队又取得一场胜利
The knicks have stolen one.
赛季最长的五连胜
It's their fifth straight win, their longest of the season.
您已经不是哈佛最有名的毕业生了
You have been surpassed as the most
famous person who is a harvard graduate.
我其实比你们更早知道林书豪
I knew about jeremy before you did.
您的意思是“林疯狂”也有您的功劳？
Are you taking credit for linsanity?
我觉得您有点这个意思
It kind of feels like you are a little bit.
我并没有功劳
I can't take credit for it,
我的意思只是，我比你们更早认识了他
But I'm just saying I was there early.
如你所说，这是很棒的故事
As you said, it's a great story.
对你来说，哪一部分最棒？
What's the greatest part in it for you?
我们取得五连胜
That we've won five in a row.
对我个人来说是这样
That's it for me.
所有的一切
Uh, just everything,
这就是体育的魅力
Just here's just what's right with sports.
从默默无闻到一举成名
He's an underdog that came up.
他很好地做到了
He does it the right way.
他够格打NBA吗？当然，毫无疑问
Can he play in the nba? Yeah, of course.
他全面，打得也很好
He's got all the tools, and he's playing really well.
那不是侥幸，他有实力
That's not a fluke, how he's playing.
当时场边有个人
I had this one dude courtside
整场比赛都在对我大吼大叫
Who was just yelling at me the whole game.
“你只能持续一周罢了”
He's like, "you're a one-week wonder."
“这场比赛你就会输了，你逊毙了”
You know, "you're not gonna win this game. You suck."
我们那场打得很糟糕
We were playing bad.
全队都很疲惫
We were tired, and I was like,
“这将是一场艰难的比赛”
"man, this is gonna be a tough one to pull out."
比赛剩一分钟时我们还落后五分
We were down 5 with a minute left.
那是一次关键的抢断
You know, we got this huge steal,
扣篮，还落后三分
Layup, down 3.
他们进攻没打成，我们有喘息的机会
They're coming down, we get a stop.
阿米尔·约翰逊那个加罚球
The and-1 at amir johnson
拉平了比分，他个人已有5个盖帽
who I believe had 5 blocks to that point, ties the game.
林书豪假投三分，改为突破
Lin fakes the 3, drives,
突进去上篮了
Goes in for the layup,
球进了，还造成犯规！
It's good, and a foul!
林书豪有机会通过罚球扳平比分
Lin can tie it with a free throw.
当时球没进
They come down, missed shot,
我们拿到球，比赛差不多还有20秒
And now we got the ball with, like, 20 seconds left.
林传给山姆波特
Lin to shumpert,
山姆波特跳投
Shumpert, pull-up jump shot.
没进，钱德勒抢到篮板
Won't go, Chandler the rebound.
尼克斯队将耗尽时间，完成最后一投
And the knicks will hold it for the final shot
24秒进攻倒计时已经关闭
As the 24-second clock is shut off.
德安东尼没有叫暂停
Mike d'antoni won't call time out
猛龙队做好了防守准备
And let the raptors set up their d.
加拿大航空中心的观众都站起来了
The crowd on its feet here at the air canada centre.
林书豪跳投
Lin puts it up.
梆！！
Bang!
林书豪，三分命中！
Jeremy lin from downtown,
尼克斯队取得领先！
And the knicks take the lead!
太惊人了！
Amazing here at the air canada centre!
只剩10秒钟，所有人都站起来了
10 seconds, everyone standing,
全场有2万人
20,000 in toronto.
拉开拉开！
Get out of his way!
让他单挑卡尔德隆！
Let him just take calderon himself!
还剩3秒钟，林书豪有身高优势
Three seconds, lin sizes him up,
干拔三分命中！
Straightaway 3, buries it!
只留下0.5秒钟
.5 remaining!
“林疯狂”还在继续！
Linsanity continues!
我对结果很满意
I'm just glad it went like this,
让林疯狂能够稍微冷却一点
So we can calm the linsanity down a little bit.
我们无法阻挡
Where we couldn't get a stop...
我梦寐以求的，就是投进这样的制胜球
That's all I dream about is hitting the game winner
再摆出搞怪的动作
And then doing some cool little dorky pose
然后帅气地走回去
And then walking off.
像我小时候那样
You know, that's, like, all I did growing up.
我一直想这么做
I always wanted to do that.
想知道那是什么感觉
I wanted to know what that felt like.
他有能力
He's got the game,
他态度很好，他很拉风
He's got the attitude, he's got the swag.
他什么都有
He's got all of that.
谢谢你们
Okay. "thank you for being..."
或者我直接开始第一部分？
Or do I just do the first part?
可以
Yeah. Okay.
嘿，书豪，呃，我是说.......
"hey, jeremy..."I mean...Whoops.
it's driving me out of my mind
（Bell Biv Devoe《Poison》的歌词）
只要拨打电话
"just dial star-star-knicks on your iphone or android phone..."
或登录尼克斯队官网
Or go to nyknicks.
can't get it outta my head
head
that girl is poison
天啊
Oh, man.
完美
Perfect.
所有印度尼西亚的朋友
"to all my friends in indonesia..."
所有新加坡的球迷
"to all my fans in singapore..."
全世界的球迷
"to all my fans around the world,
谢谢你们的支持
Thank you for all your support."
林疯狂的魅力甚至绕过半个地球到了台湾
Linsanity is catching on even halfway around the world in taiwan,
点燃了台湾球迷的激情
Even halfway around the world in taiwan,Igniting a crowd in taipei that went to a bar
他们在早上8点钟去酒吧看他的比赛
At 8:00 in the morning to watch him on tv.
（葡萄牙语）
（日语）
（西班牙语）
他把一切都处理得很好
He's handled everything very well,
像你说的，镇定自若
As you said, unflappable,
如果还要挑刺的话
（chink in the armor：俗语，带有对中国人的嘲讽意味）
But if there is a chink in the armor,
他还应该在哪些方面提高？
Where can lin improve his game?
Chink in the armor...
a chink in the armor...
很强壮，臂展很长
Nice build, he's got long arms.
这是一个合格控卫需要具备的
That's what you need as a point guard.
他实在是
And he's really, I mean...
他的眼神呢？（暗讽亚洲人的眼睛小）
What about his eyes?
迷离
Dreamy.
他的视野很好
He has great court vision.
如果不用Lin做双关语
Take away the lin puns...Mm-hmm.
结果是这样的
This is what you end up with.
令人惊“亚”
（"Amasian": amazing和asian的合体）
"amasian."
这......
now is that even...now is that even...
这合法吗？
now is that even...Is that even legal?
是的，这是林书豪
Jeremy lin. Yes, that's real.
他是从幸运饼干里蹦出来的
（幸运饼干：美国中餐厅常见食品）
Jeremy lin coming out of a fortune cookie.
这一切证明我们是多么措手不及
This whole thing has shown how unprepared
来面对这种文化
We were to deal with this culture in this context.
Floyd Mayweather（黑人拳击手）在推特上评论林书豪说
Floyd mayweather on jeremy lin tweets...
这些炒作不过因为他是亚裔
"all the hype is because he's asian.
黑人球员每晚都有他那样的表现
"black players do what he does every night
却没有得到同等的称赞
And don't get the same praise."
首先，我认为他的话是种族歧视
First of all, what he said I think is racist.
他不但可以在NBA立足
Not only can he compete and make it in the nba,
他还不断创造纪录
The guy's tearing it up and is breaking records, you knucklehead.
看看这张图，他用数学取得胜利
Check it out. "he does the math to win."
没错
yeah.
我们对亚裔的很多观念根深蒂固
For many years, we've had many stereotypes about asian-americans,
现在一窝蜂全出来了
我们还都觉得这些都是小意思
And now they're all kind of coming
out like they're no big deal.
它们很要紧
They are a big deal.
这一天终于来了
And that'll do it.
（尼克斯队）的连胜终止
The winning streak comes to an end
以令人失望的方式
In disappointing fashion,
新奥尔良黄蜂队
As the new orleans hornets
让林书豪和尼克斯队吞下
林书豪时代以来第一场失利的苦果
Hand jeremy lin and the knicks their first loss in the jeremy lin era.
现在变得更简单了
Now it's easier for me, you know.
如果有人说了种族歧视的话
Someone will say something racist,
我会一笑而过，觉得很有趣
And I'll laugh, and I'll think it's funny.
我会把所有负面的东西
Everything I get now, like, all the negative stuff,
都放到一个地方
I'll just put it in one place
然后把它们变成积极的东西
And turn it into positive stuff
让我正确地使用
So that I could use it the right way,
当我带着愤怒打球，我就会打得很烂
And when I play out of anger, I play horrible.
所以我学会控制自己的情绪
And so I had to learn how to control my emotions
然后让它随风而去
And then just, like, let it go.
手不要受伤
Don't break your hand.
你知道吗？尼克斯队的林书豪
So did you know that new knicks sensation, jeremy lin,
还有一个弟弟现在才大一，也打控卫
Has a brother who's a freshman point guard
好像是汉密尔顿学院
For hamilton college?
我们当然知道，不过就算不知道
We did, though even we didn't know
在今天的分区决赛上
That today's continental home finale
我们看到林书豪的整个家庭都来了
Would bring out the entire lin clan,
包括林书豪本人
Including the linsational jeremy himself.
我不知道他会来看我的比赛
I did not know he was coming to my game,
我在学校里确实听到有人这样说
And I actually heard from a couple people on campus like,
“嘿，听说你哥要来”
"hey, your brother's coming."
我的反应是，“不，他不会来的”
I was like, "no, he's not."
从来没有过
I've never really had that before,
我的一场比赛有那么大的关注
Had that kind of hype around one of my games.
但我觉得这并没有很大区别
But I didn't see it as that big of a difference.
不过就是家人来看我的比赛
It was just my family watching my game, so...
在“林疯狂”之前他就有来看过
I mean, he did come down before linsanity happened.
在那之前，他来看比赛时
He had come down to watch my games before that,
完全没有人会关心
And no one really cared.
过去两年
For the last, like, two years,
他在球场上一直郁郁不得志
He was never enjoying himself out there.
直到与篮网队的那场比赛过后
But that new jersey game, when things were rolling,
我第一次觉得，他在享受比赛
For the first time, he was just, like, having fun,
活在自己的梦想之中
Living his dream.
我觉得这才是“林疯狂”给他带来的，最美好的东西
I think that was, like, the best thing from linsanity.
现在最重要的问题是：“林疯狂”能继续吗？
The big question now is, can linsanity continue?
我不知道这将持续多久
I don't know how long it's gonna last,
但现在，我不在乎
But right now, I don't care.
林书豪底角尝试三分
Lin out of the corner for 3.
球进了！
Count 'em all!
如果有人说预料到这一切，那是在瞎说
Anyone who said they saw this coming is lying!
他能做到的远不止于人们以为的那样
There's a lot more that he can do
他的信心已经今非昔比
Than anybody knew, and it comes down to confidence.
林书豪突破
Jeremy on the drive.
2+1打成
And-1 for jeremy lin!
打进还造成犯规
He got the bang and the bucket.
他有自己的招牌
He's got that swagger.
他现在很有范儿
He has that "it" right now.
这超越了体育的范畴
This transcends sports. It really does.
他在当今体育界最美妙的故事里大放光芒
He has shined and evolved into the best story in sports today.
在后场施加压力
Pressure in the backcourt.
林书豪抢断，直捣黄龙
Oh, and lin the steal! To the basket!
林书豪面对德克·诺维茨基的防守
Lin, over dirk.
噢噢噢！
Ohh!
太精彩了
How good is this?
我只是想去享受比赛
I'm just out there having fun
打好球
And playing a game.
我会有表现不好的时候
I can have bad games, and, you know,
他们也许会不喜欢我，会嘘我
They may not like me, or they may boo me.
但生命中有很多事情远比篮球重要
There's a lot more important things in life than just basketball.
毕竟篮球只是一场游戏
'cause at the end of the day, basketball's just a game.
这场秀还在继续
The show continues on broadway.
这个故事有很多亮点
It's a story with many spokes.
常春藤，美籍亚裔运动员
An ivy leaguer, asian-american athlete,
从替补席横空出世
Guy off the end of the bench.
为所有没有得到机会的人代言
Speaks for everyone who didn't get their chance.
只是短短的几周，在纽约城
It's only a couple of weeks, but in new york city,
在篮球这一大舞台上
And on basketball's big stage,
他已经把故事带出了篮球这个公园
This guy has hit it out of the park.
在我身上发生的故事
What happened to me, the story that happened to me,
并不是说，我早就知道
I mean, it wasn't like I knew
我能从替补席上来完成那些事情
I could just come off the bench and do that.
我真的不知道
I really didn't.
我觉得自己有这个水平
Um, I thought I could play at this level,
我觉得自己可以成为好的球员
And I thought I could be a good player,
但我没想到会发生这一系列事情
But I didn't feel like that would happen.
有些球场上的经历
And some of those experiences out there when I was on the court,
我觉得自己是被别的力量控制着
I felt like I was being controlled by something else.
有些完全超出肉体
I felt like I was having an out-of-body experience.
我完成的一些得分
Some of the plays that I made,
我们的一些胜利
Some of the wins that we had,
真的超出了这个世界
Were just so out of this world
我时常还要掐一下自己
That I still have to pinch myself
才能相信这是真的
To really believe it.
职业生涯前9场首发比赛中
场均9.9次助攻，2.2次抢断
25.0分
在NBA 65年的历史中
这个记录前无古人
他创纪录式的表现过后
在休赛期成为自由球员
他只收到休斯顿火箭队的报价
并最终签下3年2500万美元的合同
随着林书豪翻开新的篇章
As jeremy ends one chapter and begins another,
前面的路将不断地考验他的毅力
The road ahead will continue to test his perseverance.
他的信念将永远指引他
But his faith will forever guide him.
去年我学会了
The thing I had to learn last year
完美的计划并不是
Is a perfect plan doesn't mean
所有的事情都如你所愿
That it ends up the way you want it to end up.
如果你之前问我，什么是完美的计划
In the past, if you asked me what's a perfect plan,
我可能会答，“心想事成”
I'd be like, "I get what I want,
“打好球，实现梦想”
I get my dream, I play well."
现在我有新的看法
Now I have a different perspective
关于什么才是完美的计划
On what a perfect plan is.
如果你一直赢，你不会成长
You don't get better if you win all the time.
只有失败才会让你成长
You know, you get better when you lose.
失败让你提高
You improve when you lose.
失败让你更加反思自我
You look at yourself more when you lose.
如果你我都学到很多
So if you learn a lot or if I learn a lot,
如果我有很好的成长
If I grow a lot,
如果我随着时间流逝变成更好的人
If I become a better person through tough times,
这才是神的完美计划的一部分
That's part of his perfect plan.
才是神的完美旨意的一部分
That's part of his perfect will.
如果我感到缺乏安全感
When I was going through all my insecurities
失去信心
And uncertainty and lack of confidence,
那是因为我分散了对神的专注
I was losing focus on god.
我把注意力放到别的事情上了
I was focusing on all these other things,
比如我的工作和别人的想法
Like my job and what other people thought of me
以及各种对我的报道
And what the reporters were writing.
但随着时间流逝，我会反思自己
You know, over time, I was able to check myself
找回我对神的专注
And kind of get my focus back.
我觉得神对我做了一些超自然的事情
And I think god did something supernatural in me,
一些我无法以一己之力完成的事情
Something that I couldn't do on my own,
有些我也许永远无法复制
Something that I may never be able to recreate.
所以在那件事上
So I think, in that instance,
我只是学着去奋斗
I was just learning to fight
去为了神而生活和打球
To constantly live and play for god.
如果我做到这些，我就能完成看似不可能的事情
And when I do that, I'll be able to walk on water.
上面全是《狮子王》的角色
It's all about lion king.
这里有娜娜
We have nala right here,
还有小辛巴，丁满和彭彭
Baby simba, timon and pumbaa.
林氏王朝字幕组出品
转载请注明